Thank you very much.
Thank you very much for showing up again.
That's really good to see everybody here.
So, one of the things that I've been realizing as a consequence of going through these stories is that
The degree to which they're about individuals is quite remarkable, and I think that's really telling.
Now, one of the reasons I prefer Dostoevsky to Tolstoy is because
Tolstoy is more of a sociologist, he's more interested in the relationship between groups of people.
This is an oversimplification because obviously Tolstoy is a great author, but
I like Dostoevsky better because he really delves into the souls of individuals, and I think it's remarkable
the degree to which all of the stories that we've covered so far in Genesis are about individuals.
And they're quite realistic, which is quite remarkable too.
They're not really romanticized to any great degree because all of the people that are regarded, let's say, as patriarchal or matriarchal figures in Genesis
have no shortage of ethical flaws and also no shortage of difficulties in their life.
And the difficulties are realistic.
They're major league problems, you know, like familial catastrophes, and famine, and war, and revenge, and hatred, and all those things.
It's not a pretty book, and that's one of the things that makes it great.
I mean, that's one of the things that characterizes great literature, right, is that it doesn't present you with a whitewashed view of humanity or of existence.
Existence and that's really a relief.
I think because as you all know because you're alive
There's no such thing as a whitewash existence like you're To be alive is to be in trouble ethically and existentially
I've been reading this book recently.
I'll talk about it a little bit later.
It's called better never to have been and
And it was written by a philosopher in South Africa in Cape town named Benatar.
That's his last name and
he basically argues
I Think it's a specious argument, and I think it's artificially constructed
But he basically argues that
Because life is so full of suffering
even good lives are very much full of suffering that
It's wrong to bring children into the world because the suffering outweighs the good even in good lives
and it's actually wrong it would also be better not to exist for exactly the same reason and
My sense in reading the book is that he came to that conclusion and then wrote the book to justify it
Which is actually the reverse of the way that you should write a book what you should do when you're writing a book is you?
Should have a question, and you should it should be a real question, right?
it should be one you don't know the answer to and
Then you should be studying and writing like mad and reading everything you can get your hands on
To see if you can actually grapple with the problem and come to some solution
And you should walk the reader as well through your process of thinking so that they can come to the well
Not necessarily to the same conclusion, but at least track what you're doing, and I don't think that's what he did
I think he wrote it backwards, but then and so I was thinking about it a lot because
Because, that's actually a question that I've contended with in my writing.
There are Mephistophelean, or satanic figures, for example, in Goethe's Faust.
And also Ivan, in the Brothers Karamazov, who basically make the same case, you know,
that existence is so rife with trouble, and suffering, that it would be better if it didn't exist at all.
And, the problem I've had with that, there's a variety of them,
But one of the problems I've had with that is, what happens if you start to think that way?
Because, what I've observed is that people who begin to think that way, that isn't where they stop.
Like, they get angry at existence, which is what happened to Cain, as we saw in the Cain and Abel story.
And then, the next step is to start taking revenge against existence, and that cascades until it's revenge against...
Well, I think the best way of thinking about it is revenge against God for the crime of being.
Which is, I think, the deepest sort of hatred that you can entertain.
And when you're in the grip of a really deep emotion like a really profound emotion right at the bottom of emotions
You're in something.
That's like a quasi religious state and that's more or less independent of your belief say in a transcendent deity
I mean you can be in a profoundly emotional state
That's as deep as it can be and it can have religious significance without that necessarily signifying anything about a transcendent being you know
but
But then I was thinking you see the problem with that argument is you can gerrymander it
endlessly, you know, because, first of all, how do you measure suffering and how do you measure happiness?
It's like, how do you assign weights to them?
There's just no way of doing that.
You have to do it arbitrarily.
And so, you can make an argument that the suffering outweighs the happiness, you just weight the suffering more heavily than you weight the happiness,
and that's the end of that, you know, and so that's, that's a problem.
But, I think there's a deeper problem, and I was reading this other book a while back as well, which was written by the guy
who ran the Human Genome Project, and I don't remember exactly what it was called,
but it was something like a scientist's case for God, or something like that.
And one of the things he referred to,
which didn't strike me as hard as it should have to begin with, was that he thought that one of the
Phenomena say that justified a belief in a transcendent being was something like the moral intuition of human beings that
we have a sense of right and wrong and you know it's certainly what happens in Genesis in the story of Adam and Eve is that
That that story announces the coming of the sense of right wrong right the knowledge of good and evil and it isn't something we ascribe
To animals it's something that's unique to human beings animals can be predators, and you know and they can be
gentle and you can have a relationship with them, but you never think of an evil cat or you know or an evil wolf even though they're you know they're predatory
but human beings we have this capacity to Judge between good and evil right and wrong
And it's really an integral part of our our being and I think you can make an evolutionary case for that a biological case
For that as you can make a biological case for most of what is is relevant about human beings because we're biological creatures, but
We don't really understand the significance of that like what happens in the story of Adam and Eve is that that's that
Realization that coming to the knowledge of good and evil is actually represented as a shift of cosmic significance, right?
it puts a it puts a permanent fracture in the structure of being and
You know if you think of human beings as insignificant Ants on a tiny dust mote in the middle of an infinite cosmos
a cosmos that cares less for us than who cares, fundamentally, if human beings have the knowledge to distinguish between good and evil.
But if you give consciousness a central role in being, and you can make a perfectly reasonable
case for that, because without consciousness there's no being, as far as anyone can determine,
so it may be much more central than we think, and I really don't think there's a counter-argument to that.
Like, not a solid one.
You can state that consciousness is epiphenomenal and that the world is fundamentally materialistic and it doesn't matter that there's consciousness.
You can state that, but you can make an equally credible case the other way.
And certainly our lived experience is that consciousness is crucial, obviously,
and we treat each other as if most of the time we're valuable conscious beings, and we wouldn't give up our consciousness, even though it's often consciousness of suffering.
And so then I think another problem with the book is that it's sort of predicated on the idea that life is for happiness.
And I don't think that's right, and I don't think that's how people experience life.
And I might be wrong, but it seems to me that people experience life as something like a series of crucial ethical decisions.
It's something like that.
I mean, I just can't imagine, maybe I'm being naive about this, but I can't imagine that, I can't imagine another being that's like me,
in most senses, that isn't constantly wrestling, in some sense, with what the next proper thing to do is.
It's not like it's obvious, it's not bloody obvious, and it doesn't mean you'll do the right thing.
Because you don't lot lots of times and you know that by your own judgment right because you're making mistakes all the time
Sometimes you don't know what you're doing and maybe it's a mistake and maybe it isn't and who's to say that isn't what I'm talking about
I'm talking about when you know that what you're doing is wrong
And you go ahead and do it anyways people do that all the time and that's also
Extremely peculiar you bloody well think that if you knew it was wrong
And you told yourself that it was wrong that that would be sufficient so that you just wouldn't do it
But that isn't what you're like at all you know and you can tell yourself something is wrong
50 times and you'll do it the 51st time and then you'll feel you know like like you deserve to feel probably and but it doesn't stop you and so
So then I think the other problem with the viewpoint the idea that the suffering of life Eradicates its utility is that it's predicated on the idea that happiness
Or lack of suffering even is is the right criteria by which to judge life, and I don't think that's how we Actually experience life.
I think what we do instead is put ourselves through a series of excruciating moral choices
You know and one of the things that that's really significant about the biblical stories, and I think about the the entire implicit
Philosophy you know that's embedded in the stories is that that's how life is presented in in the stories is all of these
Individuals first they're individuals not groups and second they're agonizing over their moral choices all the time all the time and they have a relationship with God and
But it's not it. It's not a directive relationship exactly even The people to whom God speaks directly which I suspect is not something you'd exactly want to have happen is
Even the fact that they have a direct relationship with God doesn't stop them from being tormented continually by their moral choices.
And so, the world is presented as a moral landscape.
Not as a place that justifies itself by happiness.
It's presented as a moral landscape, and people are presented as creatures who traverse through the moral landscape,
landscape, making ethical decisions that determine the course of the world.
And that seems to me to be right, and that's not the same as happiness, by any stretch of the imagination.
It's a whole different category of being, and, you know, and then I've thought that
through a lot, and I think, well, we do make choices, and what we do is contend with the future, you know, and that the future seems to appear to us as a realm of possibility.
a more accurate way of thinking about it than that the future presents itself to us as a realm of determined things.
It presents itself as a realm of possibility, and there's good choices in that realm, and
there's poor choices, or even evil choices in that realm.
And we're negotiating continually, deciding which of those choices we're going to bring into being.
That seems to me to be phenomenologically indisputable, and we certainly treat each
other as if that's what we're doing because we hold each other responsible for our actions you know with some exceptions and
that we're deciding each moment whether to make things better or worse and that seems to me to be correct and
I think that that's what these stories illustrate they don't say that directly you know although I think it gets more and more explicit as the narrative unfolds
but and then part of the realism of the stories is that
The people aren't the people that are being presented are by no means good
I mean, maybe with the exception of Noah, Noah seemed to be a pretty good guy
well, he did get drunk and you know and and and end up naked exposed to his sons and so forth and but I mean
He isn't talked about a lot as a character.
It's a pretty compressed story, but Abraham I mean Abraham had plenty of problems not least of which was in his inability to leave home
And then you know he's lying about his wife, and there's all sorts of mistakes, and then Jacob who we're going to talk about tonight is
An even more morally ambivalent character.
He's especially at the beginning of the story.
He's
it's it's
He isn't the sort of person that you would pick out
Especially if you were a hack writer you wouldn't pick him out as the hero of the story
He does a lot of things that are really pretty reprehensible and takes him an awful long time to learn better and yet
He's the person who's put forward as the father of the 12 tribes of Israel.
It's from this flawed person that the people that that
Maybe that whose story you might say is at the fundamental constitutes the fundamental underpinning of our culture.
It's from this deeply flawed individual that that group emerges.
And so you might think of that as a relief, too, because, you know, you're no knight in shining armor, you know, with a pure moral past.
I mean, people make mistakes of catastrophic proportions non-stop, you know.
And that also means that these stories put forward something approximating hope,
because in their realism, in their moral realism, they present heroes, I suppose,
the heroes of renown, right, the patriarchs of old, let's say, who are realistic people who have fits of anger and rage and who are murderous at times
and who are deeply, deeply embroiled with family dispute and who have
adulterous affairs and, like, they do all the terrible things that people do
and the weird thing is is that God is still with them and
you know it isn't obvious what that means or even if it means anything, but
it's very it's not disputable as far as I can tell that a we're conscious and that
Consciousness is a transcendent phenomena Which which we do not understand and that the landscape that we traverse through is moral like every story you ever watch
Watch anything that grips your imagination on the screen or in the theater like any story that grabs
You is a story of moral striving.
It's just not interesting otherwise
Right the person has to be confronted with complex moral choices
And then you see the outcome and you know the good guy does it right and the bad guy does it badly and things don't
Go so well for the bad guy Generally, and if it's a bit more sophisticated the good and the bad are in the same individual
And that's you know that's a more compelling story
but
so we could say well that lets we could make the assumption that it might be worthwhile thinking of the world as a as
It has been thought of classically as a theater upon which the forces of good and evil continually strive for dominance and I
For the life of me especially after I started reading deeply into 20th century history and all the terrible things that happened in the 20th century and all the terrible unbelievably
Reprehensible things that people did to one another I just couldn't see seeing things any other way is realistic
you know because I don't think that you can immerse yourself in 20th century history without coming to the conclusion that evil is a reality and if it's a reality
It depends on what you mean by reality, but it's fundamental enough reality for me
and if it's a reality then I don't see how you can escape from the conclusion that
that the cosmos, as we experience it at least, is a place of moral striving.
And, well that's one of the things that's really illustrated in the story of Jacob, and I found that quite striking.
So, the last time, last lecture, I ended with the Abrahamic stories, with the death of Sarah, and that was Abraham's wife.
And so we're going to continue from from there remember Abraham had a son Isaac
And he was asked by God to sacrifice his son which we talked about in some depth
and I was attempting to make the case that you know the idea of sacrifice was one of humankind's great discoveries because
It meant the discovery of the future essentially
But it also meant the discovery that the future was something that you could make a bargain with and that you could give up something
now something impulsive some pleasure even a deep pleasure in the moment and you could strive and
Hypothetically you could make a covenant a bargain with the future and if your sacrifices were acceptable and that seemed to mean
Ethically acceptable you had to sacrifice the right thing that that vastly increased the probability that not only you would be successful
let's say but that your descendants would be too and I Don't think that that's an irrational proposition
I mean you have to leaving it a bit with the realization that sometimes
you know you get sliced off at the knees no matter what right because life has an arbitrary element and and
that can't be tossed out but Building in the arbitrary element will say you still want to think well
What's your best bet given a certain amount of randomness and it seems to me that conscious self-aware
Sacrifice and proper ethical striving is your best bet and you know there's another idea
that I've always explained it when I've explained it to people I've always used
the movie Pinocchio as an example you know that when Geppetto was trying to make his puppet into a self-aware and autonomous moral agent which is
what he wants above all else you know he aims at the highest good that he can conceive
which is the star that he prays to essentially and hopes for the transformation and there's also something in that that's unutterably
Profound and maybe that is somewhat independent of the idea that you have to believe in God
I would also say that what it means to believe in God in the old testament is by no means clear and That's something. I also really want to talk about tonight.
It's not obvious what it means and well Geppetto what he does at least is Aim at the highest good of which he can conceive you know and that that's actually in a philosophical
definition of God upon occasion that God is the highest good of which you conceive and
You know that's different than The idea of a transcendent being precisely, but it's in line with it's in line with certain interesting psychoanalytic speculations
This is one of the things I really liked about Carl Jung.
You know Jung was so radical a thinker
It's just the young belief like I've read a lot of critics of you
And I've always I've always got a kick out of them because the things they accuse you of are so trivial compared to the things that Jung actually did.
That it's like accusing a murderer of jaywalking.
Like, because Jung was unbelievably radical.
Like, here's one of his ideas, you know, he thought that it was necessary.
He believed that psychotherapy could be replaced by a supreme moral effort.
And so the moral effort would be something like aiming at the good and then trying to integrate yourself around that.
And that the good at which you aimed would be something
Approximating what you would be like if you manifested your full potential and that you'd have a glimmering of what that
Full potential was so that would be the potential future you and he thought of that he thought of people as four dimensional entities
Especially essentially that were stretched across time and that you as a totality across time including your potential
Manifested yourself also in the here and now and that part of what your potential
Manifested itself with something like the voice of conscious conscience or intuition.
It's amazing idea
it's an amazing idea right because it's like what you could be in the future beckons to you in the present and
Helps you determine the difference between good and evil.
It's a mind-boggling idea, and you know I think that
It's an idea you have to contend with and then he went further than that and this is this is also remarkable idea you know he was interested in the symbolic representation
of Christ and I mean psychologically speaking and he thought of Christ as the representation of the ideal potential human it's something like that so it was
a symbolic at minimum that's what Christ was is a symbolic representation of the ideal potential of a human being and so for Jung there was no difference between
there was no psychological difference between who you could be in the future beckoning to you and the prey in the present and
orienting yourself in relationship to Christ psychologically those were the same thing and
Then so that's a pretty mind-boggling idea like seriously That's a mind-boggling idea
You know especially when you add the psychological idea that the one of the things that
Characterizes your ideal future self is the ability to make sacrifices right and the deeper the sacrifice the better and then also to recover
From the sacrifice right so that's the death and rebirth so the part of you
That's most essential to your full flowering as a as a being is
Your ability to let things go and then spring back from that so to die in some sense and to be reborn in
The service of a higher good and then well then the next part of that is that
The direction of the world depends on you doing that
So not only your own life, but your family's life and and because we're networked so intently together.
You know that the whole Panoply of humankind and maybe the structure of the of the cosmos, and you know you might think well
No, but you know it's not so simple.
It's not so simple
First of all one person can wreak an awful lot of havoc
There's absolutely no doubt about that and as we get more technologically powerful that becomes even more
Relevant and important and and and crucial you know one of the things that young said was that we had to wake up
because we are too Technologically powerful to be as morally asleep as we are and that seems to me just to be self-evident.
That's yeah for sure
That's true.
We're we're we're half asleep with nuclear bombs.
It's not a good idea.
It's seriously not a good idea and
so
Well, and then you might ask yourself too, you know, like, what is the ultimate potential of a fully developed human being?
And, well, we certainly know that you have admiration for people who are more developed rather than less developed.
That just happens automatically, or resentment, but that's okay, it's the same thing, it doesn't matter.
But it's not like you can't identify them, you can identify them, you know.
And they're put forward to you in drama and fiction and all of that constantly.
So, that's another form of moral intuition.
You know, you can discern the wheat from the chaff, let's say.
And so, the other thing that I was thinking about, that's worth consideration too, is that, you know...
Maybe this is petty, but I don't think it is.
Somebody asked me the other day if I believed in miracles.
And I hate being asked questions like that, you know.
and
You know it's also people ask me do I believe in God and like I don't know what they mean when they say that
And so I don't know what to answer because I don't think we're talked necessarily going to talk about the same thing
But in any case I said yes, and I have a variety of reasons for that, but one of them is that you know
the consensus among physicists is that But we can track the origin of the cosmos to something like a hundred millionth of a millionth of a second after the Big Bang.
It's like it's so close to the Big Bang that the difference is literally infinitesimal.
But the consensus is that before that, whatever that is, the laws of physics themselves break down.
Well, what do you call an event that exists outside the laws of physics?
By definition, that's a miracle.
Now, that doesn't necessarily mean that there's a transcendent deity that caused the event.
That's a separate issue.
But it does imply a barrier of some sort, beyond which we can't go, where some other set of rules apply.
And so, I find that interesting as well.
so
All right
so Sarah dies and Abraham makes a bargain with the
Hittites to purchase a burial place for her and they offer it as a gift and he insists upon paying for it
It's a little story that basically indicates two things that Abraham was the kind of guy that
That you trust pretty much when you see him and that even if something is offered to him as a gift
He's going to do everything to Be reciprocal about it, and so it's not a massively important part of the story
But it's it's in keeping with the same narrative flow and so
Ephron who's a Hittite offers a burial place as a gift and Abraham says no
You know you have to let me pay for it and Ephron says he will and that works out very well
And so he has a good burial place for his wife and then
Abraham decides that Isaac needs a wife and so he sends his eldest servant to Mesopotamia to find a wife for Isaac and There's a strange ritual that's performed.
So it says in the story that the servant places his hand under Abraham's thigh to to swear, but that isn't really what it means.
It means that he places his hand...
I don't know exactly how to say this properly.
Well, use your imagination.
How about that?
And the idea is that, as far as I can tell, that he's swearing on the future.
He's swearing on future people.
It's something like that.
So that's sort of what testify means, right?
Think about the root.
Well, I'm not kidding.
I'm not kidding.
That is what it...
That is the derivation, right?
It is the derivation, so, so anyways, this is a serious issue, so that servant has to go and find Isaac a good wife,
and he wants him to find Isaac a wife who is willing to accept the same fundamental belief system, which is something like the belief in a god that's a unity rather than a plurality.
you know the other thing that young was very insistent upon was that there was a relationship between poly theism and
psychological confusion and monotheism and psychological unification
I really like that idea too that you know that
That what you're trying to do because you are a plurality that that's one of the things the psychoanalysts were really good at figuring out
That the cognitive scientists haven't touched yet as far as I can tell they're way behind the psychoanalysts in that element
thinking is that you are composed of sub-personalities, which all have their own desires and their
own viewpoint and their own thoughts and their own perceptions, and they're in a war with each other constantly.
Maybe even a Darwinian war, it's been portrayed that way by certain neuroscientists.
And that one of the goals of life is to integrate all of that plurality into a hierarchical ethical structure that has some canonical ethic at the pinnacle, right?
We've talked a little bit about that, and it's not obvious what should be at the pinnacle, but we can guess at it.
It's that which we admire.
That's one way of thinking about it.
It's that that describes fair play across a sequence of games.
That's another good way of thinking about it.
It's the heroic ideal.
That's another way of thinking about it.
But it's it's combined with generosity you know because the hero the mythological hero goes out into the unknown and slays the dragon and gets the gold
But then comes back to the community and distributes.
What's found and so it's courage plus generosity and
and so all of your all of that interior struggling that you're doing is an attempt to Bang yourself against the world with challenge
Constantly to hit everything together like you're beating on a piece of iron to to to to cure it
Let's say so that
You don't you're not an internal contradiction.
You're not a mass of competing gods something like that because it's just too psychologically stressful and hard on everyone else and
impossible for them to get along with you if you're one thing one moment and another thing another moment and so
So anyways, Abraham insists that Isaac find a wife from among people who are likely to carry forward the monotheistic tradition.
And I'm not sure that the monotheistic tradition is actually indistinguishable from the individualistic tradition.
I think they might be the same thing at different levels of analysis, you know?
Because individual means undivided in some sense, right?
to be an individual means to be one thing, and the other thing that mitigates against the idea of life as happiness is that it isn't obvious to me that it's happiness that is what molds you and shapes you.
It's something more like optimal challenge, voluntarily undertaken.
It's something like that.
Right?
And I think that's echoed in the idea that everyone has a moral obligation to raise their cross, something like that, to accept the fact of their mortality voluntarily.
I believe that that's the case.
And I do actually think that that's a prerequisite to proper psychological development, because
if you're not willing to take your mortality on voluntarily, like if you're kicking and
fighting about it constantly, and you have every reason to, don't get me wrong, then you can't act forthrightly in the world.
You're going to be afraid, and when you're afraid, then you can't voluntarily take on a challenge, and then if you can't voluntarily take on a challenge, then you can't develop.
So again the life seems to be something like if it's a proper life is the voluntarily voluntary taking on of great challenges and
Maybe that's better than happiness like it's certainly more noble.
You know it's not a word
We use very much anymore the idea of nobility because we're so obsessed with happiness
But I think happiness is a like if it comes along man great.
You know wonderful don't Don't take it lightly or for granted, because it's fleeting.
But the idea that that's what you should be for, in some sense, seems to me...
If that's what life is for, then maybe it shouldn't be.
Maybe that's correct.
Because that isn't what life is.
But it also doesn't... It isn't obvious to me that that's what life should be.
You know, I mean, if you really loved someone, like your son, let's say,
Would you say well?
I hope he has a happy life, or would you say I?
Hope he accomplishes great things
it seems to me that that's better the accomplishing of great things and
because that's admirable you know it's like a happy person is a happy person, but a
Noble person is an admirable person and and that's that's better man
And so maybe there are better things than happiness
And so you can't judge being on the basis of the ratio of suffering to pleasure something like that
It's and I don't think we do that.
I don't believe we do that I mean comedians are happy right, but everyone doesn't aspire to be a comedian
And you don't watch comedy all the time even though you laugh non-stop more or less if the comedians funny
You want to get your teeth into something it also seems to me that
This is one of the reasons.
I like the existential philosophy was that
You know the existentialists believed it's sort of an original sin idea
They believed that we came into the world with an ethical burden already laden upon us something like something like that
And that we had a felt sense that it was necessary for us to justify our being and if we didn't do that
Then we weren't authentic to ourselves.
We weren't moving towards individuality.
We weren't sustaining the community
We weren't living properly and that and that that idea was deeply embedded in people as part of their
Ordinary experience and that also seems to me to be
accurate and you know I've dealt with lots of people say in my clinical practice and
They don't really cut they are they will come and say I wish I wasn't so unhappy
But they don't usually come and say I wish I was happier
And those things aren't the same and and then when when when you talk to people who are having trouble
you know they want to straighten things out and figure out how to do them right it's something like that and
And that's the primary, that's their primary goal.
So anyways, Abraham sends his eldest servant off to his, the place that God has granted him to find a wife.
And interestingly, the borders of the Promised Land are quite similar to the current borders of Israel.
And these are estimates, right, based on the biblical, and I mean that's not a fluke, obviously.
It's interesting to see the concordance between these ancient stories and the present-day world.
So, I thought that was very interesting.
And it shows, once again, that the past...
You think the past is the past, but it's not.
It's still here.
It's embedded in the present, you know.
Just like the future, in some ways, is folded up inside the present, waiting to unfold.
The past is all folded up inside the present, too.
So anyways, the servant goes to the land that he's been charged to go to, and he's trying to figure out how in the world am I going to find a good wife for Isaac?
I mean, I don't know any of these people, and so he has this little dialogue that's presented in the form of a prayer, I suppose.
And he thinks, well I'm going to go to the place where you water, where people get water, and water the animals,
Because that's a place where everyone gathers so that's a good place to find someone and and it's it's not a place of fun
and lightness and relaxation and impulsivity it's a place of Life sustaining work, and then he thinks something like well
What would a decent girl do at a watering place?
and he thought well, maybe she would offer a stranger some water and also offer to water the camels
Because that would be brave to approach the stranger and then generous and then
indicative of the willingness to make an effort and when you know that a Camel, I think he took ten camels.
There's quite a few camels anyways not just one and that a camel can drink 20 gallons of water and
Rebecca who was drawing water from the wet turns out to be Rebecca was drawing water from the well
Which is hard right because water is heavy and you have to lift it up
And it's ten camels and so that's like 200 gallons of water
so you know she has to put herself out a fair bit in order to make this stranger happy and so
That's what happens and then
The servant has brought along gifts and that sort of thing and anyways to make a long story short
Rebecca agrees to come back to come back with the servant and marry Isaac and so
Then she has she gets pregnant and she has twins and this is an interesting thing the twins fight inside her she can tell
that that they're not getting along and this is an echo right it's an echo of Cain and Abel and
There's a mythological motif that the unions have called the hostile brothers the hostile brothers
And you see them all the time Batman and the Joker are hostile brothers and Thor and Loki are hostile brothers and it's an unbelievably common Motif and
You know the ultimate hostile brothers are Christ and Satan so that's them
That's the archetypal representation of the hostile brothers right the ultimate good and the ultimate evil and so
And so it's an echo of the cain and able story
Although it's a little more complex I would say from a literary point of view because it isn't obvious Which of these brothers is cain and which of them is able they have parts of both in each of them?
So Esau who turns out to be one of the brothers and Jacob who turns out to be the other both have their
Admiral Bull qualities and their faults anyways Esau comes is born first but Jacob has him by the heel and
And so there was a fight within the womb to see who would emerge first now
That's relevant because the firstborn Had a special status well has a special status in many communities especially agricultural communities
And there's a reason all these people were more herds people
But if you divide your property equally among all your children then in like three generations
Everybody has one goat and everybody starves to death you know or the same thing happens with land
So one of the ways that that traditional communities solve that is they just give them almost everything to the firstborn and then
Everyone else knows well you go out and do whatever you can and it's kind of arbitrary and unfair
But you know at least it's predictably arbitrary and unfair instead of doomed over four generations
you know so it actually mattered to be the firstborn and and God generally favors the firstborn and
And then you might think well, what is it about being born first?
that's so relevant apart from the cultural practice of a more generous inheritance, and I would say well the firstborn is
something like the model for the leader of the family right because the firstborn child should be if there's a number of siblings a
Should take care of the siblings at least to some degree, but also should be a role model for them
So it's like a natural position of leadership, but there's a psych
There's a psychologization of the idea of the firstborn in these stories, because God often passes over the firstborn in favor of a later-born child.
He seems to do that on the basis of moral character, essentially.
And so there's this idea that, well, there's a natural proclivity towards leadership that's
just a biological fact that would be associated with being a firstborn, but there's an element of characterological development that transcends that.
And so that it's more important to be spiritually a first-born, let's say, than to be biologically a first-born.
And God recognizes that continually in these stories and inverts the natural order and
favors a later-born who's done more work with regards to characterological development.
And that's also interesting, too.
You know, I've talked to lots of business people about leadership.
And there's a literature on leadership, but it's not a good literature.
It's pretty shallow.
Because it's not that easy to define leadership and partly because there are different
You know you people have different temperaments and different temperaments can be leaders.
They just do it in different ways now
There's something in common about being a leader though
And I would say one is that if you're an actual leader you actually know where you're going
Right because what are you gonna do lead people in circles?
It's like maybe they'll follow you, but you're not a leader
You're just a charlatan so you have to know where you're going
And then you have to be able to communicate that and then people have to trust you
So you actually have to be honest because people aren't that stupid at least not for a long period of time and then
Where you're going has to have some value because otherwise why would anyone want to go along with you?
So and then you might say well, what what are the attributes then that make you a leader?
And I would say well, they're character illogical fundamentally, and this is not naive optimism or or or Casual moralizing it has nothing to do with that.
You know we know for example that that conscientiousness, the personality trait, is a good predictor of long-term success in
most occupations, not all, but most, and that one of the things that's associated with
conscientiousness is that people keep their word, they're trustworthy, and that's certainly one element of a leader, especially across any reasonable amount of time.
You have to be able to trust the person.
They can even be harsh, right, it doesn't matter, because you can see harsh leaders and kind leaders, but as long as they do what they say they will do, then you can follow
And you know that the future payoff is is is secure something like that
So the idea that character logical development is more important to leadership than primogenitor.
I think that's the right word primogenesis anyways being a firstborn
That's a very crucial psychological realization that it's character logical development that makes you favored of God
You know and I do think we've forgotten this in many ways because there isn't a lot of emphasis in our
Education system on character illogical development, and that's very very surprising to me
I think maybe it's partly because in our fractured society.
We can't agree on what constitutes a Reasonable character illogical goal, so we just throw up our hands and don't educate our kids
kids to any degree at all, especially in schools, about what an admirable person is like, or even let them know that, well, maybe you should actually try to be one, you know?
That that's actually the most important possible thing that you could learn, right?
So and I also think, and I think this is laid out very thoroughly in the biblical stories as well, is that if there are enough people who are admirable, then things work.
And if there aren't, then things are terrible.
You get wiped out.
You remember, when Abraham is bargaining with God, with regards to Sodom and Gomorrah, he asks God to save the city if there's like 40 admirable people, right?
Respectable.
But let's say admirable, right?
I don't want to say good, because good is being corrupted, in some sense, by casual usage.
I mean admirable, noble people, right?
I think Abraham bargains God down to like 10 if there's 10 of them in the city the city won't be destroyed
And that's not very many in the city
So there's an interesting idea there
Which is that there there doesn't have to be that many people in a group who have their act together?
But zero is the wrong number, and if it's zero then then we're seriously in trouble and
I think that goes along with the idea of the Pareto principle in economics, too
which is that it's a small minority of people who do most of the productive work in any given domain, but
so so a small number of Properly behaving people might have enough of an impact to keep everything moving and that might also that might actually be true
But it can't fall below some crucial level
and I do think that we're in some danger of allowing it to fall below some crucial level because
Our society seems to be at war in some ways against the idea of the individual and individual character per se
and I think that's absolutely I Think that's absolutely catastrophic, and that's part of the reason that I'm doing these biblical lectures.
You know because I think that
I've known for a long time
That the moral presuppositions of a culture are instantiated in its stories
They're not instantiated in its explicit philosophy
There might be a layer of explicit philosophy and of course there is in the west and a layer of explicit law
But underneath that there are stories, and there isn't anything under the stories except maybe Behavior you know and that's so implicit.
It doesn't even actually count
It's not a cognitive operation, and so this is the story these are the stories that are underneath our culture and so
There better be something to them.
That's what we hope and but more importantly
Maybe we shouldn't toss them away without knowing what they mean because if we toss them away
Then we are throwing everything that we depend on away as far as I can tell and we'll we will pay for it
We'll pay for it individually because we'll be weak you know because if you're not firm in your convictions
Then someone else who's firm in their convictions can you're their puppet like instantly and then you're also the puppet of your own doubts
Right because unless you have convictions
You're going to generate doubts like mad because everyone does and then the doubts win
And you'll be paralyzed because they'll be you know 50% of you moving forward and 50% of you frozen stiff
And that'll be enough just to lodge you in place and so
Okay, so there's a Psychologization of the idea of leadership which is very important and then it's associated with the idea of character illogical development
And it's associated with the idea of struggle not happiness, and it's also associated with this Abrahamic idea
which I really liked and which was something that's been very useful to me as a consequence of doing these lectures because
Remember at the beginning of the Abrahamic stories Abraham's like a stay-at-home guy, right?
He's like the guy who's 40 years old living in his in his in his mother's basement
And God says like get the hell out of there.
You know get out in the world where you belong go do something
Difficult because what you're doing isn't acceptable, and you know the first thing he does is go somewhere
There's a terrible famine, and then he goes somewhere
There's a tyranny so you know it's it's pretty funny.
He follows God's call, and it's not like sweetness and light and paradise Immediately, it's nothing like that.
It's it's instantaneous combat.
You know of the most difficult kind so but but Abraham does in fact follow that impulse, and you know it's interesting too
I mean, I don't know here's another thing that made me a really an advocate of psychoanalytic thinking.
It was the sort of thing that started to terrify me about what the human psyche was actually like.
I started to understand that not only were we like an amalgam of relatively autonomous sub-personalities,
each of which had the possibility of gaining control,
but that we were also victim, you might say,
or beneficiary of impulses that were beyond our conscious formulation or
Or or understanding or capacity to resist so one here's this here's a funny story
So I was talking to one of my patreon people online this week
And he said he's a he was a committed atheist, and that's fine
You know lots of atheists are very honest people and they're atheists because they don't know how to
Reconcile what they know with Traditional claims let's say and they're not willing to just mangle them together
You know and there might be cynicism all that associated with it as well
But he said he was he said he was entranced by these biblical lectures
you know which is pretty weird and he said if someone would have told him a year ago that he was going to like be Obsessed with the sequence of biblical lectures.
He would have told them that they were mad and
So we had a bit of a discussion about that because this is an interesting thing you know and he mentioned this he said It was something like you don't choose your interests
They choose you and that's really worth thinking about too, man
Because you know it's really hard to get interested in something you're not interested in even if you know there's a good reason for it
You know you're studying for an exam you find the material boring
Anything will be more interesting than than the studying even though you know that that's what you need to do you can't
Voluntarily grab yourself by the scruff of the neck let's say and shake yourself and say sit down and concentrate
Your mind will just go everywhere But then if you're interested in something and even if it's something you shouldn't be interested in because that happens all the time
Then it's like you're a laser focus man.
You can pay attention forever.
You can work until you're exhausted
You won't even notice it, and you remember everything.
It's like okay, if you can't control your interest what does?
And man, I tell you you can think about that for a very long time.
So Jung talked about the spirit Mercurius
You know mercury is the winged messenger of the gods and and here's how he conceptualized it psychologically
He thought this is what the ancient people
Who thought about mercury as the winged messenger of the gods we're trying to state psychologically you know your your interest flits around
It's like there's something that captures it and that moves your interest from place to place
You know like if you walk into a bookstore, you'll get interested in a particular book
It's as if the book grips you because you don't know why you're interested in that you might but often
You don't know why you're interested in that book
And you know your interest is flitting around and so that's mercury the thing that makes your interest
flicker around is Mercury, the winged messenger of the gods.
And Mercury is the messenger of the gods because it's the things behind the scenes, psychologically, that are manipulating your attention.
And for Jung, those were equivalent, in some sense, to the lost gods.
And so, for Jung, your interest was being manipulated behind the scenes by unseen forces that were associated with your characterological development across time.
That was the manifestation of the self.
So the self is this... the potential you, let's say.
And the way it operates in the present is by gripping your interest and directing it somewhere.
And that's part of the instinct of self-realization.
It's a mind-boggling idea, man.
Really, it's...
I think it's correct.
I can't see how it can't be correct.
It doesn't mean I understand it completely, but it certainly seems phenomenologically correct, and...
I mean, the potential that you are has to manifest itself somehow, in the here and now.
It has to and what better way than by directing your attention
You know it's like it seems like this might be useful for you, or maybe you get attracted to this person
Maybe you admire this person that happens with kids a lot
They'll admire someone and then copy them and you can see that that's obviously part of their developmental progression, right?
It's a form of hero worship, but kids are very imitative and they hero worship at the drop of a hat and so they're they're entranced by
The the next stage of development and if they see someone who embodies that especially if it's in the zone of proximal development
It's it's some it's something they could achieve
Stretching a bit they find someone who embodies that next stage of development
And then they start to imitate them and act like them well.
We're adults are no different.
We're no different
We're just we do it at a perhaps more abstract and sophisticated level so okay, so
Jacob and Esau are are
Hostile brothers.
They're they're like Cain and Abel except the mixture of Cain and Abel, and they're very different
Esau was red and covered with hair.
He was a hunter and a man of the field so he's like your basic chalk, right?
He's extroverted.
He's outgoing.
He's really tough.
He's like extraordinarily masculine
he hunts and he's a real favorite of his father and so and and Jacob isn't he's a dweller intense and
Yeah, right exactly
Exactly exactly right and it says Isaac loved Esau, but Rebecca loved Jacob now
That's a problem right that that's a big problem
and that there's a freudian element to this is like this family is now divided because
One child is the favorite of the mother and that's Jacob and one child is the favorite of the father and so Jacob is kind
of a mother's boy, I guess to use in our rather archaic phrase and
And, certainly not as admirable from his father's perspective as Esau, who's a tough guy who goes out with a bow and arrow and like, you know, wanders around in the plains and brings animals home, and he's tough.
He's a tough guy.
So, and, but there's this discord in the family, because one parent prefers one child and the other parent prefers the other, and it's obvious from the story that the parents do not communicate about this, because they really take sides, and so there's a split in the family.
And that's I think very realistic because one of the things that you do learn if you have a family and of course most of you do
but if you also think about families is that there's there's deep divisions within families very very frequently that no one will ever talk about and
or even think about often because it's too painful to think about you know and Freud himself said Freud was clearly his mother's favorite and
And the family sacrificed a lot, including some of the potential ambitions of the other children,
in order to kind of put Sigmund Freud up on a pedestal, and advance his education.
And it worked!
I mean, you know, he turned into a great man, but there was a cost to his siblings.
And Freud himself said that there was something about being the favourite of the mother,
that gave a person additional confidence throughout their life.
And, you know, there's something to be said about that.
Even someone like Eric Erickson you know he noted that very interested in child development that first bonding with the mother
Was the was the place where trust was established maybe trust even in the goodness of existence was established and so anyways Jacob is
Rachel's favorite and
Esau is Isaac's favorite
now Esau Being extroverted.
Let's say is also a bit impulsive and maybe he's not
He's a man of action.
He's not a forward thinker and
but he's also doing hard work, and so you know he goes out and he's hunting and he's worn out and
he comes home, and he's faint with hunger and
Jacob is at home cooking.
He's boiling up lentils red lentils and
you know Esau comes in from the hunt and he's like half starved to death and he's sitting there and
and the aroma of these red lentils reaches them and
he's exhausted and and and
He tells Jacob that he wants some of this stew and Jacob
Who's being a pain in the neck?
fundamentally
They've basically says no
there's a there's a teasing thing going on here and and won't give him any and and and there's
You have to imagine this because it's not laid out explicitly in the story but there's some dispute about whether
Esau gets to have lunch and Jacob finally says well, I'll give you some but you have to you have to give me your birthright and
You think Esau you think he must say something like you know well to hell with it
Take it.
You know you son of a bitch take it.
Just give me some damn stew
It's something like that, so that's what happens
But you know with these archaic people once you made a statement like that that was you were done
That was it and so Esau sells his birthright and this turns out to be incredibly significant Benson who wrote biblical commentary said oh
there's a bit of a twist to it so Esau eats the the red lentils and then from then on his name is red and
You've got to use your imagination a bit.
I mean People are making fun of him right that's why they're calling him red
I mean he's already red because we established that but no one was calling him red before this and so for the rest of his life
You know every time he goes out amongst his friends and family they call him red and sort of snicker because he's the you know
Half famished idiot who sold his birthright for a bowl of lentils and so it's it's not it's not that funny
Actually, and so Esau is not happy about this and and it actually turns out that this so what does it mean?
It means don't sell the future for the desires of the present and don't be casual about what you have
And then there's an archetypal element to this too and Benson says various have been the opinions what this birthright was which Esau sold
But the most probable is that together with the right of sacrificing
So determining what should be sacrificed and when and being the priest of the family it
included the peculiar blessing promised to the seed of Abraham that of being the progenitor of the Messiah and the
and the error of the special promises of God respecting Christ's kingdom.
It was at least typical of spiritual privileges, those of the firstborn, that are written in heaven.
Well, that's a lot harsher than meets the eye to begin with.
And so, there's a very interesting, deep moral story there, which is...
It's sort of, Esau does the opposite of a sacrifice.
It's the reverse, right?
He sacrifices the future for the present.
And so the story basically says, the way it's laid out across stories,
is that if you're the sort of person that sacrifices the future to the present,
then that eradicates the possibility that you will bring the most noble being into existence.
That's what it means.
And you can again.
This is the psychological significance of the biblical story
So that's a bad thing to do if you want to realize your potential.
Let's say you don't do reverse sacrifices
That's a very bad idea and so Esau really did himself in by being too attached to the present without a vision of the future so he's too in the moment you know and
And he pays a heavy price for it
I mean he's the first of all he loses his birthright and and his double inheritance
So there's a practical consequence, and then there's a spiritual consequence
And then he's well he's been made a fool of by his brother Jacob means
Supplanter by the way
That's what the name means and Jacob is always trying to usurp Esau as we see and so Jacob gets one over on him
And you know that's not doesn't make an older brother happy when a younger brother gets something over on him
That's for sure, and then he loses the opportunity to be the progenitor of the messiah
Which is like he probably didn't realize that precisely, but it seems to be you know.
It's kind of rough that so
Then there's there's a statement in Matthew 16 26 for what is a man Profited if he shall gain the whole world and lose his own soul or what shall a man give in exchange for a soul
It's an echo of the same idea.
You know when you think well
What is this idea of soul mean and it's not intellect and it said it's something like
It's something like consciousness allied with character
I think and I think the reason that it's valued so much is that because you got to ask yourself
Well, what do you really have when it comes down to it?
So life is suffering let's say and you know you can
You can pile up
Worldly goods and the God in the old testament doesn't seem to have anything against that really right the people who he favors
seem to prosper quite nicely in the world, but they also have to make a choice between whether they're going to
fundamentally sustain their character or whether they're going to prosper in the world when push comes to shove and the idea constantly is that really what you have in the world that
allows you the best possible defense against the suffering that's intrinsic to being is your character.
That's what you have
Period.
And I don't think there is anything that's more psychologically true than that.
You know because everything else well first of all your relationships with others depend on your character
And certainly this is part of the story of Noah's ark.
You know because his generations were perfect, so we had a very tight familial
Arrangement everyone trusted each other that's a big deal if you hit a rocky patch in your life, right?
And it's character that it's character that determines that you know if you're generous and honest and all of those things and people know they can
Rely on you assuming.
They're not resentful.
That's a whole different story.
Then they're going to come to your aid when when it's necessary
They're going to pull together with you
And you know when people are really after you for one reason or another and they're accusing you of all sorts of things
And you're guilty because you you have a past that's laden with character logical errors
then it's very easy for people to take you down because they'll poke until they hit a place where you're guilty and
Then you're done because you'll do yourself in with your own judgment and so
well, so Iso makes a very big mistake, and
there's a sacrificial idea here too, which is, you know, now and then you're going to be faced with a situation where it's something you really want, or your character.
Maybe you'll have to lie about something, you know, and
you'll think, ah, what difference does it make?
You know, I'll lie about it.
Jacob does this.
But the problem, there's a bunch of problems with that.
One is that, that well now you know that you're the sort of person that will in fact deceive yourself about the nature of reality if Something shiny is dangled in front of you
And that's not good because it undermines your faith in yourself
And when you're really in trouble they call that the dark night of the soul when you're really in trouble
That's what you've got you've got whether or not you can trust yourself
And that's it you know when things are really harsh
And so if you've betrayed yourself in that manner, then you weaken yourself under the worst possible circumstances
And that's just that's really not a good thing
so
This is very practical advice
It's not casual moralizing.
There's very little casual moralizing in these stories
In the next part of the story there's some parallels with Abraham, and that's built into the narrative.
I think because Isaac is Abraham's descendant and so we have to keep the narrative echoing forward
otherwise it loses its its continuity and there's a famine in the land that
Isaac's in and God tells him to stay the course anyways repeating the promise he
he gave to Abraham although Isaac goes to Abimelech also telling the king
and people that Rebecca was his sister which is exactly what Abraham did when
He went to egypt and so there's another echo there of the same the same
It's as if the story is being told for a second time essentially and that's supposed to remind you of the of the previous story
but they're careless the king sees that Rebecca and Isaac are intimate together and
Luckily he doesn't have them put to death
He just tells everybody in the kingdom that they're to be left hell alone, and then isaac prospers in that land just like
Abraham did in Egypt until the Philistines asked him to leave.
He's just getting too rich and powerful.
Things are going too well for him, so he's asked to he's asked to leave.
Now in the meantime Esau gets married, and this is a funny little story.
He says he marries two women who give grief to Isaac and
Rebekah, so they, whoever Esau marries, they're not popular with his, with their in-laws, not in the least.
That actually becomes relevant a little later because
They drive Rebecca quite mad so I get a kick out of that because that's very common.
You know it's not easy to
Integrate new people into your family and and hope that that will go smoothly
It's actually one of the real catastrophes in life right you have a kid
Maybe you get along with them, and maybe you don't
but let's assume you do, but then they marry someone that you just don't like and
Or maybe you think is wrong for them.
I mean that's really rough
That's what are you going to do about that you know because you're you're basically screwed both ways
if you have the person you love around then you have to put up with this horrendous creature that they allied themselves with and if
You if you get rid of them completely well, then you know you don't have your child anymore
So it's very very difficult position, and so that's another example of the realism
I think of the stories now isaac who's hypothetically on his deathbed asks
Esau to hunt for venison because he likes venison and he's happy that his son is a hunter and Rebecca overhears this
So she conspires with Jacob to to slaughter two small goats and
make his father some stew because he wants Esau to make him stew out of venison, but
Rebecca who's being I would say let's say slightly deceitful or horribly lying that would be more accurate
She conspires with Jacob so Jacob kills two little goats kids and boils up a stew and then he puts on some goat skins because Esau is a hairy character and and
Rebecca dresses Isaac in Esau's clothing because Isaac can't see very well at this point and so then Jacob goes into his father with the stew and
he's trying to disguise his voice, but it doesn't work very well and
And so Isaac asks him to come close and Jacob puts out his arm with the goatskin on it
And and Isaac smells him too, and he smells like Esau and which maybe wasn't the best thing, but
And feels like him and and so
Because Isaac thinks he's on his deathbed
he decides to deliver a blessing to
hypothetically to Esau and so
But it's Jacob and so you that's a big deal too because the blessing is actually as I said before with these ancient people it
Appeared as though once you said something you didn't get to take it back
You couldn't say well look you you deceived me, so it doesn't count
it was like I did they weren't maybe as
Well weak might be one way of thinking about it
But another way is they weren't quite as attentive to
Context you know because if I make you a deal, and then it turns out that you've betrayed me
I may feel that the deal is no longer valid because
The assumption was you were being honest to begin with and that you know violates the whole spirit
But that isn't how these people thought they said once you promised man you promised and that was that
so Isaac blesses Jacob he says
Let God give you the dew of heaven and the fatness of the earth and plenty of corn and wine
Let people serve you and nations bow down to you.
Be lord over thy brethren."
That's going to be rough on Esau.
Let thy mother's sons bow down to thee.
Cursed be everyone that curseth thee, and blessed be he that blesseth thee.
And so there's a quite a remarkable painting of that.
So there's Rebecca.
She's looking pretty old and
Isaac's looking pretty blind and
Jacob's taking directions from his mother and we might say he's perhaps a little old to be taking moral lessons from his mother especially given And how she's acting
And how she's acting and so it's a pretty ugly scene all together especially that we also know that Jacob
Already tricked Esau out of his birthright and so now he's like taking the birthright and he's taken the blessing and so as I said that
Jacob he turns out to be the father of Israel.
It's like he's a reprehensible character.
These are major league
Betrayals that he's engaging in it's not trivial.
He really
really
Pulls the rug out from under his brother, and you know you could say well
Esau is not as awake as he might be you know he's kind of a wild man and fair enough
but it certainly seems to me that the Predominant moral error falls on Jacob's shoulders.
It's very treacherous behavior what he's doing
so then Esau shows up, and he's got a nice stag for his dad, and it's like a Little late for that
And he states that his brother was rightly named Jacob which means supplanter
Because he's been deceived twice and Isaac says Isaac answered he's asking fun.
Yes.
I was asking fundamentally if there's anything at all left over for him and
Isaac can't give him the same blessing because that's already been given so he has to think of something else and
Isaac says behold I've made him thy lord and all his brothers
I've given to him for servants which includes you and with corn and wine if I sustained him and what shall I now do unto?
My son and Esau said unto his father have you even one blessing for me my father and blessed me also
And Esau lifted up his voice and wept and you know we already know that Esau is a pretty tough guy by all appearances and
you know he's out there hunting on his own and camping and it's like he's no pushover and the fact that this reduces him to tears
is an indication of the magnitude of the betrayal and
Isaac says behold thy dwelling shall be the fatness of the earth and of the dew of heaven from above and by thy sword thou
Shall live and thou shalt serve your brother and it shall come to pass when you will have the dominion
And you'll break the yoke his yoke off from thy neck and Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing wherewith his father blessed him and
Esau said in his heart the days of mourning for my father are at hand then I will slay my brother Jacob
So fundamentally you know if Isaac dies or when he dies then we'll mourn for him
And then Jacob better look the hell out because it's like it's it's serious
Death coming his way, and you know he's got a he's got a point
He's in Dante's inferno.
I think I mentioned this at one point, so Dante's inferno.
It's a very interesting story
it's a descent into hell a and
It's actually one of the places that we sort of derive the popular conception of hell was partly based on Dante's on
Dante's imagination on his work and what Dante was trying to do was to discover the hierarchical structure of evil
And you know you might think there's a hierarchical structure of good some things are better than other things
But there's also a hierarchical structure of evil some evils are greater than other evils and he put betrayal in the in the in the lowest part of hell
Right so if you were betraying people you were right beside Satan himself, and so and I think that's good
That's very smart.
Well Dante was a genius after all
And I think the reason for that is that you see if someone trusts you
They're laying their vulnerability open to you now.
They might just be naive
Let's say and that's we won't think about that because you're just a child if you're naive you can still be betrayed
But if you're an adult and you trust it's often because you if you're an actual adult
It's you willingly open yourself up knowing that you could be hurt right because you're not naive anymore
so you decide to trust and you say I'll open myself up and
I know that I'm laying myself open to you if you choose to use that power
And then that's a good thing to know, you know, if you've been hurt as a child, or hurt as a naive person, you might say,
well, why should I ever trust again?
Which is a really good question.
And the answer is, the reason you trust again once you're an adult is because you're courageous.
You're courageous.
It's an act of courage to trust.
And the reason it's useful is because, if you trust someone, you open the door to reciprocity and negotiation and cooperation.
And you entice the best part of the person forward.
And so it's a it's a courageous act
But then if you betray someone then what you've done is you've taken the best part of them
Which is the part that will courageously trust you know with open eyes right and you've stuck a dagger in that and so you've
purposefully damaged the best part of them and so that's why it's such a egregious fault and and
It's often people don't recover from that sort of thing you if you betray someone badly enough
You can you can damage them like you can give them post-traumatic stress disorder
If you really if you really put your mind to it
And you know that's not just a psychological disorder if you have post-traumatic stress disorder it produces permanent neurological alterations that make you more
Neurotic more sensitive to negative emotion really for the rest of your life like you can you can recover
From it to some degree, but stress will tend to reinstantiate the PTSD so you you hurt someone and it's not merely cycled not
not that psychological is merely but it's not merely psychological right it's it's fundamental physiological damage so anyways Jacob's smart enough to get out
of there and which is also not really a testament to his integrity right I mean he's done these terrible things at the behest of his mother because he wants
power and and he wants to get it without deserving it and then you know he finally goes too far and he hightails it out of there to his to another family
member to his mother's brother and so it's not exactly the world's most heroic story that's for sure and so now there's an interlude here and this is a
really interesting interlude it's the story of Jacob's ladder so he's off to visit Laban, or Laban, who's his mother's brother.
And on the way, he has a sleep.
And he lighted upon a certain place and tarried there all night,
because the sun was set, and he took of the stones of that place and put them for his pillows,
which seems to indicate very bad planning on his part, and lay down in that place to sleep.
And he dreamed, and beheld a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven, and beheld the angels of God ascending and descending on it.
And behold, the Lord stood above it and said,
I am the Lord God of Abraham thy father, and the God of Isaac.
The land whereon thou liest, to thee
I will give it, and to thy seed."
And so this story of Jacob's ladder has really possessed the imagination of the West.
And then there's a reason for that.
It's because it's an archetypal story, because the idea of a ladder that reaches to heaven is one of the oldest ideas of mankind.
So you find it widely distributed among the shamanic cultures for example, and it's a hallmark of psychedelic experience
That's another way of thinking about it.
Which is a very peculiar thing, so there's one Representation of the ladder you see God up at the top there Peeking out from the clouds now
You know that's sort of where we get the idea That God is in in heaven and then heavens up in the sky and and that's an easy
story to make fun of because you know we've gone up to the moon and there's no God there and and but but this this is not a reasonable way of conceptualizing
what these experiences are about these experiences what this is the opening up
there that's more like an opening into an alternate dimension that's a better way of thinking about it it's beyond like from from the Judeo-Christian
perspective one of the things you have to understand is that God is beyond space and time.
He's not in the universe.
He's outside the universe in some manner.
And so, the idea that you have an experience of God and it's up isn't... the up is the best that the human imagination can do with what's essentially a form of extra-dimensional experience.
Or that's the best way to conceptualize it.
And these experiences aren't rare, you know.
They make up the core of the shamanic tradition.
And so, there's an intrusion of the ancient shamanic
Tradition which is tens of thousands of years old into the biblical stories at this point now
Why Jacob had a essentially shamanic experience is very difficult to tell because we don't know what these old people were up to right?
and we don't know how much of the Archaic tradition Archaic religious tradition was still extant at that at that point in time
But we certainly do know that our ancient forebears
We're using psychedelic substances constantly like Amanita Muscaria mushrooms for example
Which were widely used in India before they became extinct
That's the theory anyways that seemed to be the basis of the chemical Soma which much has been written about and so
We hear of this as a dream or as a vision and perhaps that's what it was
but perhaps that wasn't what it was either and perhaps it was an experience that was induced by by
by the same processes that shamanic people have always induced these experiences.
And so we're going to go through this a little bit.
Anyways, there's a connection between heaven and earth that opens up.
That's the vision.
And there's messengers moving up and down.
Now, one way you can conceptualize that is psychologically, as we already discussed,
that there are forces within you that are active and alive,
And you can think of them, in some sense, as messengers of the higher self.
And so you could think about this as an image of a psychological reality.
But...
And so we can stick with that, but...
Here's some of the representations that have been made.
I really like the one on the right.
That's William Blake.
I like the helix idea.
And I don't think that that's...
That's fluke.
There are helixes and double helixes, and all sorts of imagery.
Very ancient and very modern that are associated with both healing and with this kind of vision
So and you see it in the blake representation God is associated with well really with the sun and with light and and you see that on the left as well that
Wherever God is is where light is and so that's a very interesting idea as far as I'm concerned as well
There's some other representations
One by Chagall.
So now there's this idea that there's the possibility of opening up a line of communication between the human psyche and the transcendent divine.
And there's a great image of Christ as pantocritor, so creator of the world, that is one of the first mosaics, if I remember correctly, and I wish I remembered where it was, but I don't.
But it's a very interesting image.
I'm having a carving of it made at the moment by a friend of mine, but
You see Christ's face Portrayed in a medieval manner, and he's holding a book so it symbolizes the importance of the book
you know as a means of transmitting wisdom and his face is very asymmetrical and
The eyes are different one side and the other and one half of the face
represents the human part and the other side of the face represents the divine part
And you know I also think about that psychologically because I do think that that's
The right way to conceptualize human beings is that there's an aspect of us
That's mortal and human and limited, but there's an aspect of us
That's transcendent and divine as well, and it's latent in some sense
But there are times when it manifests itself, and this is not speculation
Right this is like the oldest experience of human beings now
It's not necessarily an easy experience to have but it's reported everywhere
And it can be reliably induced as we've discussed before by chemical means which and I don't know what that means exactly
We've talked a little bit about psilocybin mushrooms for example
And you could say that the mystical experiences that have been invoked in the newest experiments down at at Johns Hopkins are
Derangements or forms of psychosis you know because they have some similarity to psycho-psychotic experiences although
So, psychotic people were given LSD in the 60s, and they always said that that was something different than what they were having.
And if you give psychotic people amphetamines, you can make them worse.
So they're biochemically separate, and we know that.
But also, the thing that's so interesting about the psilocybin experiences is that they reliably produce mystical experiences
that the people rate as among the most important experiences of their life.
And, among those who have the psychedelic experience, positive things happen to them.
And so that kind of messes with the whole psychosis theory, right?
Because, what are you gonna do?
You're gonna claim that you give someone a pill, and they have a psychotic break, and then they're healthier.
It's like, no.
That isn't how psychotic breaks work.
You're not healthier after having one.
You're, like, you're a broken egg, and it's not easy to put you back together.
So, and we know that people all over the world have discovered every manner of psychedelic substance that you could possibly,
well you imagine there's lots of hungry people wandering the earth for a long time and they ate every damn thing they could get their hands on.
Now and then something very peculiar happened as a consequence.
So, so I'm going to tell you a little bit about the shamanic tradition because it's associated with Jacob's ladder.
Um, according to Iliada, Mercia Iliada, he was a great historian of religion, a compatriot of Jung's, and they influenced each other quite substantially.
Iliada believed that shamanism that used psychedelics was a degeneration from the original, more pure shamanism,
but I think later scholarship has demonstrated that that's incorrect, that the shamanic ritual per se was a direct consequence of the use, discovery of, and ritualistic use of psychedelic substances.
But anyways, Iliadah identified three pathways to shamanism, and the shaman in it, in a tribe, was more educated than the typical person, with a larger vocabulary.
And was the repository of the oral tradition.
And so, learned all the stories that had been passed down word-to-mouth.
And people, by the way, are very, very, can very, very accurately tell the same story across generations.
That's been quite well-documented
So and and people who can't read really can remember because what else are they going to do?
Their memories are far greater than modern people's memories because we can forget everything because we can just look it up
but they remembered things because they had no choice my father knew someone who was a
illiterate and and and and couldn't use numbers either when he grew up in Saskatchewan, you know
Sixty years ago, and he was a he had sheep if I remember correctly and although he couldn't count
He knew if one of his sheep was missing because he knew all the sheep
And so he could tell just by looking if one of the sheep was missing, but he couldn't count and so
Well, so people who don't have our particular set of skills first of all they're not stupid and second
They have other skills that we don't understand to fill in the gaps so Eliade identified spontaneous vocation
So you were just you have the spirit of a shaman let's say so you're probably extremely high in openness
Let's say from a modern perspective hereditary transmission
So you know your father was a shaman and your grandfather was a shaman and so forth and you got initiated into that process or a personal quest
In Siberia this is from Eliana in Siberia the youth who is called to be a shaman attracts attention by his strange behavior
For example, he seeks solitude, becomes absent-minded, loves to roam in the woods or unfrequited places, has visions and sings in his sleep.
You know, if you put someone in a place that's deprived, that's where you're deprived from a sensory perspective, normal people will hallucinate quite quickly.
So it seems what happens is that if you dampen down the sensory input, then you start to become aware of the background processes of your mind.
It's something like that.
It's like the signal to noise ratio.
I got to get this right.
As the noise decreases, some of the noise becomes signal, the background noise becomes signal, and you start to become aware of your own internal psychological processes.
It's something like that.
He has visions and sings in his sleep.
In some instances, this period of incubation is marked by quite serious symptoms among the Yakut.
The young man sometimes has fits of fury and easily loses consciousness, hides in the forest, feeds on the bark of trees,
Throws himself into water and fire and cuts themselves with knives
We went to a potlatch in Northern on Northern Vancouver Island about a year ago
And they had this one dance it was the Kwakwaka'wakw
natives and they had this interesting dance that was the dance of the wild man and so
the person who invited us was the wild man, and he was dressed up in in
Tree branches and so forth and so he was the person who'd been in the bush too long
And he came in as a cannibal and there there was
Genuine cannibalistic rights among these people not so long ago
He came in as a cannibal and everybody had to wear this like cedar headdress because if you had a cedar headdress on then
The cannibal wouldn't take a bite out of you
And they actually took this rather seriously
So you should have your cedar headdress on and so he's looking around the crowd
And there's like 400 people in this place, and he could really act too
So he's doing this wild man dance and then all the women stood up and started to
Kind of dance in place and sing and they were taming him, so that was really cool
You know it was really interesting to see that because those people are about they've had an unbroken culture for about 13,000 years
Say that's how long they've been out Island there, and it was very interesting to see that dramatization of the domestication of of man by women
Women laid out in that dance in that way
But it was also interesting in relationship to the shamanic tradition because he came in as a wild man right and he had to be
re-civilized in some sense and brought back down to Earth
so
But by whatever method he may have been designated a shaman is recognized as such only after having received two methods of instruction
The first is ecstatic dreams trances visions the other thing that this guy told me and I have no
There's no reason to doubt him.
He's also not a literate person.
And so has a great memory.
He does carving, traditional carving.
And he's very good at it.
He carved a 53-foot totem pole that's now in front of the Museum of Art in downtown Montreal.
So if you ever go there, you can go see it.
It won't be there forever, but it's there right now.
And, uh,
he was taught to carve by his grandparents
and he said that
he dreamed in, you know, you know what the Haida images look like, so the Kwakwaka'waks are kind of like the Haida, same sort of imagery.
He told me that he dreamed in those images, so when he dreams, that's the form that the
things he dreams about takes, and he also said that he would talk to his grandparents in his dreams, so if he was working on a piece of wood and trying to figure out how to carve it, and he
ran into a particularly difficult problem, he'd dream, and he'd have a conversation with his grandparents, and they'd help him figure out how to solve the problem, and then he'd wake up and he could go carve the...
And the thing is he told me these things sort of matter-of-factly right like you know you know what I mean, it wasn't like
He was telling me these weird things that happened to him although.
He was doing that to some degree.
I asked him a lot of questions about what he carved and what it all meant and
You know that was just part of his explanation of how he did it
and he he carved me a couple of doors that I have in my house and
And one of them is quite interesting.
Well, the two make a panel and
They're an underwater scene and under the water
There's a bunch of you know mythical monsters some of them are killer whales
And I think there's an octopus down there and carved in this particular style
And he said that the other thing that happens to him when he dreams is he goes down to the bottom of the water where?
These mythical creatures are and he gets inspiration from them, and so I thought that was extremely interesting, too
You know we we don't know what a mind that isn't hyper civilized.
Let's say
Hyper literate like like our minds are because we're so bombarded by external stimuli
We have no idea what the natural mind is like really and so it was quite interesting to
To to listen to that and and also to see the consequences because he's quite a great.
He's quite a great carver
So the first is ecstatic dreams transits visions the second is traditional shamanic techniques names and functions of the spirits
mythology and genealogy of the clan a secret language this twofold teaching imparted by the spirits and the old master shamans constitutes initiation
Well, so you know modern people have a problem with that because we don't really get initiated, but I would say that
You know, let's say that we're each on a quest of some sort.
You wouldn't be here, I don't think, if you weren't, because why else would you be here?
And so you're on a quest of some sort to figure out, to struggle with the meaning of life,
let's say.
And you don't want to do that alone, because you only last like 70 years, and good luck figuring it out on your own.
It's just not going to happen.
It's too complicated.
And you'll be too isolated, right?
If it's just you, that's insanity.
No one can stand that.
And so you hope that other people have things to tell you, and that your culture has something to tell you.
You know, so you're on a quest, maybe not with the same intensity as a shamanic initiate,
but you know, let's give you some credit.
And then you're also trying to understand the wisdom of the past, and that's the second part of this.
It's like, okay, well you're a human being, and human beings have been telling stories
for a long period of time, trying to figure out what's going on, trying to figure out how to orient themselves in the world.
And so, you know, partly what you're doing here is exactly what the shamanic initiate does in the second part of the process, which is to expose yourself to the degree that you
can to names and functions of the spirits, mythology and genealogy of the clan, and the secret language.
This twofold teaching, imparted by the spirits and the old master shamans, constitutes initiation.
So that's a rebirth, right?
That's what initiation is.
It's being born again, and that's a birth of the spirit rather than of the body.
It's something like that, and so it's the rebirth of an integrated psyche.
That's one way of thinking about it, and a psyche that's individual, but also grounded in common humanity, in the wisdom of common humanity.
And that makes you strong, or at least it makes you stronger, because there's a limit
to your strength, but God only knows to some degree what that limit is, you know.
People can be unbelievably tough.
Unbelievably tough.
And I think it's even the more admirable for human beings to be tough, because we're so conscious of how we can be hurt.
And we're so conscious of what that hurt can lead to, you know, you can have your family taken away from you, and you can be destroyed.
And the fact that you can be courageous in the face of that at all is something that is absolutely unbelievable, right?
And people deserve a lot more credit, I think, than people give themselves.
Because the fact that we can be honorable under conditions of life and death, right,
of suffering, that's a testament to the human spirit.
And there's a profound anti-human ethos, I think, that pervades our culture, you know,
that considers human beings cancers on the planet, something like that, you know.
And that there should be less of us.
It's the same spirit that motivated the guy who wrote the book about it better to have never been.
I don't see it that way, you know, I mean, I think people do pretty well for
You know, for having their leg caught in a bear trap and their head caught in a vise
They're actually doing pretty well because life is really hard and the fact that we're not
Absolutely brutal and murderous all the time is really something remarkable given what we actually have to contend with that we can go out of our way to be honest and generous and
Altruistic and to care for each other under unbelievably dire circumstances and to act nobly sometimes under the most trying conditions.
You know, in Solzhenitsyn's Gulag Archipelago,
he tells story after story of people who acted abysmally, but also people who, under the worst threats imaginable, never sacrificed their character.
You know, and reading about that is really...
Well, it really makes you wonder.
That's what it does.
The future shamans among the Tungus, as they approach maturity, go through a hysterical or a historoid crisis,
but sometimes their vocation manifests itself at an earlier age.
The boy runs away into the mountains and remains there for a week or more,
feeding on animals which he tears to pieces with his teeth.
He returns to the village, filthy, blood-stained, and it's only after ten or more days that have passed that he begins to babble incoherent words.
The strange behaviour of future shamans has not failed to attract the attention of scholars,
and from the middle of the past century, several attempts have been made to explain the phenomena as a mental disorder.
But the problem was wrongly put, for on the one hand it is not true that shamans always are or always have to be neuropathic, mentally deranged.
On the other hand, and this is the critical issue, those among them who had been ill become shamans precisely because they had succeeded in becoming cured.
So it's not the descent into this strange subterranean psychological state that constitutes the transformation that makes the shaman, but it's the emergence back out of that.
out of that, and that's a journey to the underworld, and a rebirth, right?
And so, and there's this great book,
this is a great book, by a guy named Henry Ellen Berge, and he was an existential
psychoanalyst and philosopher, and he wrote a book called The Discovery of the Unconscious, which I would highly recommend.
It's on my list of recommended readings.
It is a great book.
If you want to know about the psychoanalytic tradition,
it's the best introduction there is, and he discusses Adler and young and freud and does a very credible job of all three
but also takes the history of psychoanalytic thought back three or four hundred years before freud and so it's it's very engaging reading and and
And and very interesting and one of the things alan Burge points out quite
Clearly is and he associates this to some degree with the shamanic tradition that both freud and young young in particular underwent very intense periods of psychological disturbance let's say.
And I would say what was happening is that because they were questioning their axioms at the most fundamental level, they were deranging their cognitive and perceptual structures, right?
And Jung was also experimenting with imaginative techniques, with visionary techniques, which he did a lot.
And there was a period of his life where he was
having a constant stream of visions, which he wrote down in a book
called The Red Book, but at the same time he was still functioning as a
psychiatrist and operating normally in the world and so you know people have
suggested that what he had was a psychotic break but that's ridiculous
because you don't don't that's not how it works man if you're having a
psychotic break you you're not being an effective psychiatrist those things do
not go together especially not for a long period of time and so there there's
the possibility of extreme experience without psychosis psychopathology and so
and
Ellen Berge he says much the same thing about freud and about Charles Darwin as well who underwent a terrible period of Mental
Confusion I would say as a consequence of Formulating his theory of evolution which was really hard on him because he was a he was a die-hard
Christian and he knew what he knew what the implications of his theory were he didn't know what to do about that you know
So it was very very hard on him
So it's quite common for people of genius to go through an intense crisis psychological crisis
But then resolve it and the genius is in the resolution, right?
The precondition for the genius is the dissolution in some sense because you have to be obsessed with the problem
It has to grip you completely before you're going to concentrate on it
so obsessively that you might come up with a solution, but it's the people who come up with a solution that are the
Prophets and the shaman and so forth and so on and and and so that's not this isn't something that only characterizes archaic cultures
we just don't recognize it in our own culture properly and and
That's a problem
Well sometimes we do
Right you remember that in the lion king right that Rafiki shows up.
He's the shaman he brings he brings a
Simba down that tunnel dark tunnel that's the dark night of the soul
He has him reflect upon himself in a pool when he reflects upon himself deeply
He sees the reflection of his father then that becomes a core thing of cosmic significance and his father appears in the sky
Just like God appears to Jacob and basically tells him that it's time for him to grow the hell up and to return to the Devastated Kingdom and to set it right
You know and so and that's right.
That's exactly right.
I mean we live in the devastated Kingdom
That's an eternal truth, and it's the responsibility of the individual to grow the hell up and to set it right
because when it's devastated and when things are not in place then everyone suffers too much and
That's not good, and there's no excuse for not doing something about it because you don't have anything better to do
so
and even like children's movies tell you this so
So, this is a fun one.
This is from the Eadwine Salter, 9th to 12th century.
That's Adam and Eve, but there is speculation that the fruit that they're eating there, you see, is psilocybin mushrooms.
Because they're the only kind of mushroom that grow like that.
So that's pretty wild, you might say.
And then, this is the, I think it's called Banisteria Vine, if I remember correctly,
and it's what ayahuasca is made out of, and it has this double helix form, which is very, very interesting.
And the natives, nobody could figure out how the hell they made this ayahuasca, which transports people spiritually in a very intense manner.
And there's a whole religion based on it, like a modern religion as well as the archaic religion.
To make this stuff, they had to take two plants that don't grow anywhere near each other,
Like there's like a million plants in the Amazon so like how do you figure that out nobody knows then you have to cook them?
In this very particular way for a particular amount of time before you produce this stuff
So one of the plants has DMT in it
Which is a very intense psychedelic, but it's very short acting and the other has an MAO inhibitor
So if you take the DMT and you take the MAO inhibitor
Then the DMT trip lasts for much longer and so that's what these
Amazonian natives figured out and no one has any idea how they managed it
And if you ask them they tell you that the plants told them how to do it
Which isn't much of an explanation as far as modern people are concerned
But then when modern people take the ayahuasca and the plant so to speak starts to talk to them
They're a little less leery of the whole theory that the plants had something to do with this, so you know and these things
That these I'm loath to talk about this because I'm not an advocate for drug use
But by the same token you can't ignore empirical data.
It's not reasonable
And the empirical data that psychedelic substances can produce mystical experiences and that those often have a transformative effect
I mean one of the latest studies showed that if you took people who were dying of cancer
And you and you gave them psilocybin in a sufficient dose to produce a mystical experience that you radically it decreased their their fear of death
it's like
You got to think about that man.
That's
that's
Tough that's a tough experiment.
You just wouldn't expect that that you think you take someone you deranged them
Intensely and then when they come back, they're not even though they're dying They're not nearly as afraid of dying
you know you got to kind of wake up and smell the roses when you see something like that and the people who are Doing this research are very reliable people so
There's the Amanita muscaria.
You know there's this old idea.
It's quite a funny idea toadstools, so
So, flies like Amanita muscaria, and there's some, this is ridiculous, there's some evidence
that they actually like getting stoned, so, because animals will eat these, like reindeer
will eat these things too, and they get pretty tripped out by them, and so I have this book
on psychedelic use among animals, which is a small book, but, and so, so there's this
idea that toads used to sit around the Amanita muscaria and wait for the stone flies to like
buzz badly around them and then snap them up, so that's pretty funny, I think, and so, and
you know, there are mushrooms in the US that are the oldest, the oldest organisms on the planet, hey, there's one mushroom
I can't remember where it is, but it covers something like, oh God, I don't know, like square, hundreds of square miles
it's like this huge thing, because it's all underground, right, and they have these very complex networks of
Mycelia they're called and they think the thing is like a hundred and fifty thousand years old something like that, so
There's plenty of things about the world that we don't know that's for sure
There's the chemical makeup of the classic psychedelics you see they all have the same fundamental structure
This is serotonin.
That's the one of the major brain neurotransmitters
and so what happens with the psychedelics is that they they alter the they alter the brain function by altering the the neurochemical utilization of serotonin
and change the manner in which the serotonergic systems work
and the serotonergic system is a very basic system
because when you're an embryo and your brain is developing
it's the serotonin projections that basically orchestrate the development of your brain
so they're, and they're very archaic circuits, very, very archaic circuits
so
and this is the paper, I think I stole this from Psilocybin Griffiths who's been doing a lot of this research psilocybin can occasion mystical type experiences having substantial and sustained personal meaning and spiritual significance
Psilocybin Griffiths who's been doing a lot of this research psilocybin can occasion mystical type experiences having substantial and sustained personal meaning and spiritual significance
so
Why?
That's a good question right like so so here's a question for you
It is beyond dispute that human beings are capable of religious experience
Why?
Why is that exactly and they're like you can associate with psychosis?
But that doesn't work because the theory doesn't hold the theory doesn't hold water.
It's not the same thing
So why is it there exactly?
And it's not an easy thing to figure out like I've been trying to figure
I'm always trying to figure out a biological explanation for everything right because
If you want to find something to stand on you want to make sure that it can resist a challenge
And so if I can find an explanation for something that's reductionistic and materialistic and biological then I'm going for that
That's a tough one
Consciousness is a tough one the moral sense is a tough one.
They're not easy things to crack the big bang is a tough one
so
You know I mean a cynic might say that maybe
Sometimes when people are close to suicide they'll have a mystical experience you know and you maybe you say well
It's a last-Ditch attempt of your brain to delude you into thinking that your life has some significance significance you know and that's a plausible theory,
but I Don't think it accounts for the generality of the phenomena
so
So I don't buy it
What happens in the shamanic?
Experiences that the shaman has the experience of being reduced to a skeleton first
so death, a death experience, a very realistic death experience, and then the next thing that happens is that
he finds himself in a place where he's communing with his ancestral, the ancestral spirits, and
then after that there's the climbing of something like the ladder, Jacob's ladder say, and an encounter with God for all intents and purposes, and it's very widespread
It's the world tree, and I've thought about this a lot, trying to figure out what this represents.
According to a Yakut informant that's in Siberia, the spirits carry the future shaman to hell and shut him in a house for three years.
Here he undergoes his initiation.
The spirits cut off his head, which they set off to one side, for the novice must watch
his own dismemberment with his own eyes, dissolution to the primary elements in some sense, and
hack his body to bits which are later distributed among the spirits of various sicknesses.
It's only on this condition that the future shaman will obtain the power of healing.
His bones are then covered with new flesh and in some case he is also given new blood.
So there's a death and resurrection experience that's associated with the shamanic ritual.
We're here in the presence of a very ancient religious idea which belongs to the hunter culture.
symbolizes the final root of animal life, the mold from which the flesh continually rises.
It is from the bone that men and animals are reborn for a time.
They maintain themselves in an existence of the flesh, then they die, and their life is reduced to the essence concentrated in the skeleton from which they will be born again."
That's a good graphic representation of the experience.
That's an old painting by I think it's Hieronymus Bosch if I remember correctly
I really like that because it's it's reminiscent of the near-death experiences that you hear people describe, and they're quite common as well and and
I Had that very weird experience once I don't think I've told you this story.
I was I Was assessing someone who had gone through a car windshield, and he was very depressed
It had happened a long time before but he was very depressed and the insurance company was basically accusing him of
Malingering because he'd been depressed for so long and you know he'd sort of healed up and everything
But if your left hemisphere is damaged especially the frontal part of your left hemisphere
Then you can be in a chronic state of depression because the left hemisphere
Generally speaking is responsible for positive emotion
And so if it isn't there then it's like negative emotion for you
And so I went and assessed him, and I was giving him this
I think it was called the MMPI, the Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory, which is a kind of a standard half personality test, half psychopathology test and
He was filling it out.
He was a very serious guy, middle-aged guy.
Nothing about him was New Agey in the least
He was like an accountant.
I think I think in fact.
He was an accountant if I remember correctly
and
There's one question, and it said my spirit has left my body I
Think that's right.
It's very close and he stopped and he asked me well.
He said I'm not sure how to answer this and
So I said well why and he said well after I went through the car windshield
I was in a coma for three weeks something like that, and I died.
I think he said he died three times and
He said that he could remember
He couldn't remember anything during that period of time, and he couldn't remember the car accident.
That's retrograde amnesia
It's quite common with head injuries, and he said that during one of those
experiences, and this is all he remembered from the hospital, was that he came out of his body and
went down the long tunnel of light, you've heard these near-death experiences, and then saw his family members there and
Saw the heavenly light and then realized that it wasn't his time and came back to his body
Now what was interesting about this guy was that well first of all I didn't ask him about this right
He basically volunteered this story, and it was instigated by this question and and
He didn't know that anybody else had any ever had an experience like that because I asked him if he'd ever heard anything about like
That he said no that was interesting, but what really was interesting is how the hell did he remember that?
Right, because he had amnesia during that entire period of time.
He was in a bloody coma.
It's like he didn't remember anything.
He remembered that.
And so,
well, those experiences are more common than you think.
And then there's a, you know, there's a painting of one
which is quite interesting, and that's like a tunnel to heaven.
It's the same basic idea.
It's a little bit more suffering going on in this one, I think, but that's pretty much typical of Hieronymus Bosch.
I mean, I don't know what was up with that guy, but
he was he was one strange character now the scandinavians have this idea that
the world is a tree and I've been thinking about that a lot I think that
the tree idea the tree is something that is grounded in in matter let's say and
that reaches up to heaven in the Scandinavian tree at the bottom there's
quite a cool idea at the bottom of that see this tree is constantly being nod by
Snakes you can sort of see the snakes at the bottom and at the same time
It's being watered and the water makes the tree grow at the same rate that the snakes gnawed its roots
So it's like a yin-yang idea
You know that there's continual chaotic destruction and replacement at the basis of whatever this process is
but the tree seems to me to be a representation not so much of
It's like a different dimensional space.
That's that's what's trying to be represented so imagine that you know you're structured
If you take powers of 10 magnification, say human beings are about in the middle of the tiniest thing and the largest thing
If you do it by powers of 10
And so, you know, you have a subatomic level and an atomic level and a molecular level
And, you know, then a, maybe a level of organs
And then there's you and then there's your family
And so on, all the way up the tree, fundamentally
And so I think that what this tree represents, and this is the thing that the shaman moves up and down,
I think that's what it represents.
It's this different view of
its dimensionality.
It's something like that.
And I think that what happens in the psychedelic experience is that consciousness can travel up and down that structure.
It's something like that, and maybe not only up and down it, but maybe right through it.
I know that's a radical claim.
It's a really radical claim, and it might be wrong,
but it's probably wrong even because most radical claims are wrong, but
But but I'm not so sure it's wrong
And here's something cool
So that's the Scandinavian world tree and that was drawn
By an anthropologist who visited the tribes in the Amazon who use ayahuasca
Now you see it's a snake.
It's a tree with snakes
Well, you know that's reminiscent of the story in Adam and Eve obviously, but it's also reminiscent of our
Primate dwelling place right because that was basically our ancestral home a tree
Surrounded by snakes and the snakes like to eat us, and this is a long time ago.
This is like 50 billion years ago
It's really a long time ago, and so we don't know where these images come from precisely
but I do have the suspicion that that we used the circuitry that we developed to detect snakes to represent
the unknown as such because like a snake is something that comes out of the unknown and like we evolved right we all evolved out of an animal substructure
and so we had to get our our biological cognitive structure from somewhere and
we have this capacity of thinking about the absolute unknown and the terrors
that are involved in that that the horrors that can emerge from what we don't understand and it stands perfectly to reason that we would use circuits
that were already pre-developed for that and that this is a reasonable
representation of the existential structure of the world so and I think I might have showed you this before but it never ceases to amaze me this this
picture so my son drew this when he was nine eight and so on the right you see mushroom houses and
They have the names of all his friends on them and so that's order right and then on the left side you see
Chaos there and that little orange thing is a bug and then there's a river that runs right down the middle and so that's like
the yin yang symbol with the divide in the middle that's quite cool, and then there's there it is.
There's Jacob's ladder
It's like Jack and the Beanstalk which is by the way another variant of the same shamanic story and
There are bugs going up and down it and they're taking messages from heaven and then up there in heaven
It's got the sun and there's St.. Peter, and I don't know where in the world he got this
It's not like he had a lot of religious education.
I mean really despite me
And you know there's the pearly gates up there
And then that was the world as far as his he had a very well-ordered psyche
I would say and and still does but when he drew that it just absolutely blew me away, and so I had it laminated and it's in my office because
Well, I don't know because like what the hell do you make of that?
You know that's that's why
so
Well, you sort of get the picture there.
You know the cathedrals the great cathedrals of Europe are
They're like the forest in stone right and they try to represent the light coming through the leaves
And so it's sort of our ancestral forest home
But it's it's transformed into these great sculptures of stone
And you know they produce awe because of the combination of light and darkness and color
But also I think for the same reason that huge trees produce awe in people you know and we don't want them cut down they seem sacred in some sense and perhaps they are
but
you know it also seemed to me this is an intuition that the The architects of these great cathedrals were trying to get, they're trying to express something that's deep and structural.
They're trying to express the idea that if being was constituted properly, then it would be organized from the subatomic level all the way up to the highest cosmic level perfectly.
So every layer stacked on top of each other without any contradictions.
That would be an ideal mode of being and everything would come together under those circumstances.
And that's what's being expressed in these cathedrals.
It's not all that's being expressed, because they're also shaped like a cross.
And, you know, the idea is that the center of the cross, which is the center of suffering, is also the place of the individual, the place where the transformation takes place.
That's all built into the architecture as well.
And so, then there's the tree-like structures that make us up.
It's stretched down to the tiniest realities,
microcosm and there's this this idea it's all represented in the same way again it's this idea especially the Mandela up in the top right it's the
idea of this perfection of crystalline structure and that's what the yogis are trying to attain when they organize their bodies they're trying to get every
single layer of their being aligned properly and it's something like you can kind of see an echo of that in the I think that's a Tibetan sand painting if I remember correctly, on the bottom left.
The idea is that if you get yourself a line properly, then information can flow along that tree that's you, without without impediment, something like that.
And that would be like a state of optimal health.
And that both physical and spiritual exercises can put you in that state.
And that's, well, those are all clouds of ideas that surround this idea of a ladder to heaven.
And so Jacob is talking to God, and God says, Behold, I am with thee, and I will keep thee
in all places where you go and bring you again into this land, for I won't leave you until
I have done that which I have spoken to you of.
And Jacob awakened out of his sleep, and he said, Surely the Lord is in this place, and
I knew it not.
And he was afraid and said, How dreadful is this place!
This is none other but the house of God, and this is the gate of heaven.
And Jacob rose up early in the morning and took the stone that he had put for his pillows and set it up for a pillar and poured oil on top of it.
That's a sacrifice.
And he called the name of that place Bethel, but the name of the city was called Luz at the first.
And Jacob vowed a vow, saying, If God will be with me and will keep me in this way that
I go, and will give me bread to eat and raiment to put on, so that I come again to my Father's
house in peace, then shall the Lord be my God.
And this stone which I have set for a pillar shall be God's house.
And of all of that, that is given to me, I will surely give the tenth unto thee.
And that's a pretty good place to stop.
So, now, I'll just...
...conclude.
So, you have this very morally ambivalent character, right?
Who's, so far, pretty much everything he's done, that we're familiar with, is not good.
so he's he's betrayed his brother horribly twice badly enough so that he his brother wants to kill him and
Everyone can kind of sympathize with his brother
so and then he runs away essentially because his mother tells him to which is not exactly a testament to his character and despite that
Strangely enough he has this experience you know and that's heartening.
I guess and that's the point is that
that people are predisposed to terrible error.
There's no doubt about that.
And yet, when I was writing my latest book, I had a friend of mine.
Norman Deutsch wrote the foreword.
And Norman's written a couple of great books, and he's Jewish.
And he read some of what I'd written, and he took me to task for making the God of the Old Testament,
know, from a Christian perspective, too harsh and unforgiving.
And I rewrote a fair bit of it because of his criticism and because of what I've learned doing these lectures.
It's like, it's not exactly right, you know.
I mean, what happens in the Old Testament is if you screw up, especially if you know you do
and you decide that you're not going to do anything about it, so it's conscious
and deliberate, then, like, look the hell out.
You are in serious trouble.
And I actually think that's also psychologically accurate.
One of the Jung pointed out and this always struck me was that if you don't know what you're doing
This is actually in the gospel of thomas as well interestingly enough as one of the gothic Gospels Christ tells his followers something like
If you make a mistake, and you don't know what you're doing, then you'll be forgiven for it
but if you make a mistake knowing what you're doing and you do it anyways then like good luck to you and and I think that's I think that's That's psychologically accurate I mean
I mean, one of the things that's very interesting about the judgmental God in the Old Testament, however, is that he can be bargained with,
and even if you make mistakes, especially if you're unconscious of them, if you haven't learned yet, let's say, then you always have the opportunity to return to the proper path.
And that's- people get cynical about that, because there's, you know, this mostly Christian idea that you could live a terribly sinful life,
But if you repented on your deathbed, it's like heaven for you, and it's like oh, that's that sounds like a great deal, right?
It's like you can do whatever the hell you want until just before you die of course you might not know when that is
So that's a problem you then you can just say well
I'm sorry
And you know everything's forgiven, but the problem with being cynical about that sort of thing is that it's no trivial matter to repent
you know because to repent means a a figure out what you actually did and the worst things that you did the more horrible it is to figure it out
It's no joke right and there's no genuine repentance without understanding of the depth of your depravity and so
If you've lived a particularly reprehensible life, and you come to understand it
I think that in and of itself could kill you you know it's a terrible thing to Wake up and see what you've done if what you've done is truly terrible
So there's no easy out.
It's not an easy out.
It's just pure cynicism to associate that idea with an easy out.
It's not.
But there is that positive idea that's continually represented is that the individual is the source of moral choice.
And the individual is prone to genuine error and temptation in a believable and realistic way.
That that doesn't sever the relationship between the individual and the divine and the possibility of further growth
And then I would say well
Thank God for that because without that like who would have a chance right who would have a chance and so The idea that the deity has presented the infinite
Let's say as presented in the old testament is merely judgmental is definitely wrong and and is in fact something that you can Contend with and bargain with I'll close with one thing
one of the things that I learned while I was going through this was the meaning of the name Israel
because Jacob Eventually gets named Israel, and and I'm jumping ahead a little bit to the next lecture, but
Israel and so he's also the father of Israel and the father of the 12 sons who make up the 12 tribes of Israel, but what Israel means is he who struggles with God and
that's such an interesting idea because it's again a psychological idea and
And that's why I said earlier that it isn't obvious in the Old Testament what it means to believe in God, because what Jacob does is struggle with God.
And I think that that's a really good characterization of an ethical life, because if you're trying
to lead an ethical life, that's what you're doing, is you're struggling.
Like blind belief isn't helpful, because you don't know what you're believing in, like it's just not that helpful.
But if you're possessed by the desire to orient yourself properly, but also confused by the existential structure of the world, which we all are, then what you're doing
when you're trying to orient yourself properly in life is struggling ethically.
And Jacob actually gets quite hurt.
He wrestles with God, literally, and God dislocates his thigh.
And so, you know, the idea there is, watch the hell out, right?
The thing that you're contending with is powerful, although you can contend with it.
That's the thing that's so interesting.
But you know, you do it at some genuine peril, which I think is exactly right.
But the idea that Israel
So there's Israel the state, let's say, and Israel the promised land, and all of that.
But there's this more important idea, which is again a psychological idea, which is the state of Israel, which is the promised land, is the state that everyone who wrestles with God exists in.
And that's not happy, naive belief in, you know, an eternally blessed afterlife.
It's not that.
It's not a wish fulfillment.
It's to be actively engaged in life, in the difficulties of life, right?
And trying to find the path, because that's what wrestling with God is, is trying to find the path.
And that seems to me what belief means fundamentally in the Old Testament, and perhaps in the New testament as well is that
Belief is expressed in trying to find the path and that's an ethical struggle, and it's a real struggle
It's the struggle of life, so as long as you're willing to engage in that struggle then hypothetically you have the divine behind you and
so I believe that I think that's true because the other thing I see is that the people who set things right so that
that the horrible forces of cosmic destruction don't do us in, the people
who are trying to set things right are the ones that are struggling ethically.
And so, and that, there is a redemptive element to that.
And I don't think there's any way of being cynical about that.
So, well, so thank you, Will.
So remember to speak right into the mic, because there are all these other
people watching that will hear that will hear us so okay hi dr. Peterson so with
the story of Jacob today there was a theme of betrayal and you can see that
from the beginning because he was very angry and jealous at his brother and I
was thinking are there any stories or what can say about betrayal that does
come from a loved one right where it's not from a place of so black and white
of anger resentment and bitter and how do the parties kind of recover from that
Or is there any way to rename that or is it as black and white as if you betray someone then there?
It's like Jacob where he was bitter.
He was hatred no and in fact in this story.
It's not black and white because we know we're only halfway through it and
One of the things I've noticed as a clinician let's say is that and as an observer of people in general is that I've never ever seen anyone get away with anything and
Jacob doesn't get away with any of this and so
So, you know, he's humbled by his eventual experiences, and he learns that he did it wrong.
And there's reconciliation that happens throughout the story of Jacob.
And there's minor betrayals and major betrayals, you know, that some of them have tremendously
serious consequences, and some of them have lesser consequences.
But there is an underlying idea that things can still be set right, even though it's  well,
I think it takes Jacob some 20 years, something like that, to set things right.
And even then, it's like touch and go.
So did I answer your question?
Okay.
Yeah.
Hey.
You speak frequently in your lectures about, I guess, the war between good and evil, or
the struggle of life, really, is a struggle between good and evil being at the core of a conscious, lived existence.
And I guess on that note, if you were 100% certain that there was no afterlife, would
you still be able to preach that there's a positive meaning in life?
If you were 100% certain, some atheists seem to be 100% certain, and yet they still preach
that there's some positive meaning to life, would you be one of those?
Or would you turn into Cain, you know, so cynical?
I think that, well, as far as I'm concerned, one of the things I learned from studying 20th century history is that
like, even if the idea that, even if you take the most cynical of ideas, let's say, that life is
irredeemable suffering, and perhaps isn't even justified because of that,
it still seems to me that you have an ethical duty, let's say,
to live in a manner that reduces that to the degree that that's possible.
And so, and I think that that can be experienced as meaningful, in some sense, independently of the transcendent context.
Now, I don't exactly know how to strip off the transcendent context,
because one of the things I would say that's happened to me is,
because I've spent so much time looking at the horrible things that people have done,
is that it's, like Jung said that, this is one of his famous quotes,
he said, no tree can reach up to heaven unless its roots reach down to hell.
And so, as I've dug deeper into the depravity of human beings, my sense of the possibility of human beings has also grown, what would you say, in proportion, until I've become
convinced actually that good is a more powerful force than evil, even though evil is an unbelievably powerful force.
And so I can't really strip the transcendent away now.
bearing that has on eternity, say on an afterlife, I mean, I can't say anything about that.
The only thing I guess I can say is that there are many things about being that we don't understand in the least, and we don't understand the nature of consciousness or the nature of time.
So I wouldn't despair about that, but yes, I think that life can still be meaningful without there being a necessity of an afterlife.
Could you get through one lecture without using the word transcendence, though?
No, no.
No.
Hi, Dr. Peterson.
So since studying your work, one of the things
that I find most fascinating is your analysis of the story of Cain and Abel.
And my question is, if Cain got to the point
The point that he did right before killing his brother, murdering his ideal, and decided that that was something he didn't want to do.
What advice or guidance would you give a person that got to that point?
Well, there's a story I read called The Cocktail Party.
I've mentioned this before by T.S.
Elliot, and in The Cocktail Party there's a scene, it's a play,
where this woman approaches a psychiatrist and starts talking to him about her problems.
And she says something that surprises him, she says,
I hope that I'm the problem.
And he says, well why would you hope that?
And she says, well I've thought about it a lot, and if the world's the problem, then I'm done,
because I can't change the world, but if I'm the problem, then maybe there's something about myself I can change,
I can undo this terrible situation that I'm in and so I would say that's repentance
fundamentally, it's like there if and I say this carefully because I understand that people are susceptible to bad fortune
Sin and ignorance can make that worse, but independently of that like good people suffer make no mistake about it
but if things aren't right for you, if you're resentful about being, because that's the right way of
Because that's the deepest way of thinking about it.
If you read the writings of the people who do the mass killings for example
That's what you see over and over.
It's Cain.
It's like they're angry beyond comprehension at the Intolerability of being and they're angry at God, even if they don't say it exactly like that
They come so close to saying it like that that it's there's no difference
you know what God says to Cain is look to yourself first before you criticize being and
That strikes me as right.
It's because to not do that is arrogant beyond belief that's satanic arrogance
Literally if something like that can be literal.
It's like don't make yourself the judge of being before you clean up your
Oh, your room, let's say.
Because the other thing too, this is something I learned in some part from Solzhenitsyn, when he was in the prison camps and trying
to understand how these heroic people he saw could possibly manage it, one of the exercises he undertook, and he really viewed this within a
Christian Orthodox context of repentance and redemption, is he said he went over his life with a fine-toothed comb and tried to
imagine all of the ethical mistakes he made in his entire life that he knew were mistakes, right?
It was a soul search, he wasn't relying on external standards of morality, except in so far as were inevitably influenced by those,
and then his idea was, is there something I could do right now to put that right?
And that's the right question, like if things aren't going your way, and
And I think that means that you're resentful and arrogant and deceitful.
Those are the three things that clump together
I think that that constitute the core of evil at something like that, and so if you're possessed by that which is a hell
Then it's repentance
That's the right answer and what that means is you have to figure out what you did wrong
And you have to pay for it, and then at least you could think well look I can try that with all of my soul
Let's say and see what happens
Right?
It can at least be an experiment, and then I would also say that that's an act of faith.
It's an act of faith to conduct that experiment, because you put yourself on the line, right?
And that's what an act of faith is.
You don't know the outcome,
but you don't know the outcome of your life.
So to live, in some sense, is an act of faith.
You're putting faith in something.
That's why you're moving forward.
You couldn't move forward without an act of faith.
You know, and people say, well, I only move forward on the basis of the facts.
It's like yeah, but you select the facts and there's an infinity of facts, and they don't just tell you what to do
So it's not a credible answer
So if you're in that situation, it's like
Look to yourself
You know and one of the things about Solzhenitsyn that's so bloody amazing is that's what he did
and then he wrote the Gulag Archipelago, and you know he took an axe to the intellectual and moral substructure of of the totalitarian communist states
so while he was redeeming himself let's say he was simultaneously redeeming the world and
You see something like that like you you got to wake up man.
That's
That was really something
so
Yeah, Dr.. Peterson
I have a lot of questions that arise from your comments at the bell for 100 event your m103 video your recent discussion with Ayaan Hershey Ali and your comments on Islam in the west in general and
And in your comments there's this common theme that one of these things is not like the other.
You put the Judeo-Christian tradition on the one side and Islam on the other.
Specifically the quote complex problem of Islam and the quote as a quote totalizing system.
Before I go further let me state that if hypothetically a final analysis of Islam resulted in as total a denunciation as your analysis of postmodernism or neo-Marxism,
I wouldn't be personally offended at all.
This isn't a personal question.
In your recent interview with Ayaan Hirsi Ali, she said Western values are superior to Islamic law and Islamic values.
I agree with that, basically, certainly in the context of, let's say, current global affairs.
I'll skip the quotes from her Reason magazine interview, but you should read them,
because hers is a worldview which is very much the West versus Islam.
Not radical Islam, but Islam, including necessarily the military option.
So my question is, at the level of psychological significance of these stories, at the level of mythology and archetype,
and archetyped, how is Islam so different from the Judeo-Christian tradition?
You know, because Adam, Adam, Eve, Hava, Satan, Shaitan, so on and so forth, everything from the fall to the flood,
a lot of what you've discussed in this lecture series is necessarily part of Islam as well.
And in fact, I think one of the strongest criticism of Islam is that it's perhaps pretty unoriginal.
You know, tonight you said that the moral presuppositions of a culture are instantiated in its stories.
I see a lot of the same stories.
So current global affairs aside,
I'm asking at the deepest levels how different are these stories and the moral presuppositions?
Okay, well that's that's a killer question
well
okay, so the first thing I would say is fundamentally, I don't know and
So part of the reason that I'm one of the things I'm planning to do is to have a series of discussions and plenty of people
Have contacted me about discussing with Ayaan Hirsi Ali as you know she has as powerful and serious foes, and they're not happy with her black and white distinction.
And so, now I read Infidel, and I really liked that book.
My sense was that she was a heroine.
Now what that means in relationship to Islam, that's a different story, because she came out of a totalitarian, let's say, family structure in a relatively totalitarian society.
And you could make the case that there's a correspondence between that and Islam, and
you could make the case that there isn't, and of course that's the critical issue.
And so, there's a couple of things that I can't wrap my head around with, wrap my head around easily in relationship to Islam.
And so one is what I see as the failure to separate church from state.
And that's a problem.
Now it may not be a problem as such, but it's certainly a problem in relationship to the relation between Islam and the West, because we separate church from state.
Now there's fundamentalists in the United States, Christian fundamentalists, who think that that separation is a mistake.
So it's not only an idea that's rooted in Islam that those should be united.
But it's definitely a problem with regards to our co-existence, because that's a fundamentally different presumption.
So that's problem number one.
Problem number two for me, and again this may be a consequence of my ignorance which
I'm trying to rectify, Muhammad was a warlord.
And I don't know what to do about that fact.
Like one thing you can say about Christ, hypothetically, let's say, I'm not talking about a historical reality necessarily, although I'm not denying it either, is that of all the things he was,
Warlord was definitely not one of them.
And I don't know what to do about that.
And so I don't know how to reconcile that.
And I don't know how to reconcile, like, not only was Muhammad a warlord, which I don't
think is an unreasonable thing to proclaim, the expansion that he initiated was unbelievably successful.
I mean, within 600 years, it was the biggest empire the world had ever seen.
And it demolished Byzantine Christianity, which is something that Western people don't even know.
You know I've read thinkers who said that the west was so traumatized culturally let's say by the demolition of Byzantine Christianity that we can't even study it now and
so I don't know if that's true, but I don't know that it's not true either and
The Buddhists were wiped out of Afghanistan and we saw that echoed in the Taliban's destruction of those great Buddhist monuments and
so
So what I'm hoping is that there's a bridge there better be a bridge and that's why I want to have these discussions because I'd like to
understand if there's a bridge and so lots of people have sent me people who I should talk to who they think represent Islam far better than Ayaan Hirzi Ali and
Perhaps they're correct and hopefully I'll get an opportunity to talk to them because I would like to know why I would like to know if what I think is wrong
Because if it's wrong, it's important that I know it's wrong
but At the moment.
I don't a I don't know it's wrong and B. I don't see I'm not sure what it signifies
So and I don't think anyone is sure right because we have this entangled
Entangling of the civilizations you know when there's other things to like I'm not very happy with the saudi arabs and the wahhabis
I Don't think there are allies I don't see how any western woman can possibly think that there are allies and
I'm not happy with the fact that the petrodollars that we send them are transformed in substantial part into
The kind of propaganda that's definitely a threat to the west, and I'm not very happy with the fact that our politicians appear
Stupidly blind to that now that may again be a consequence of my ignorance.
It's certainly possible but those are the sorts of things that
That I can't reconcile and so
You know, I've seen, I've also seen parallels between the ideas that I'm presenting here and other religious traditions, Taoism, Buddhism, Hinduism.
It's harder for me to bridge the gap with Islam, and I'm not sure why that is.
I think it has something to do with the things that I just laid out.
Now, what I don't know about Islam would fill very many volumes, many of which I have sitting on my shelves at home right now,
because I want to do the reading, you know, as I progress through this.
Good evening, Dr. Pearson.
Thanks for continuing this series.
Even us atheists appreciate the interaction and the conversation.
I wanted to ask you something that is both emotional and analytical because oftentimes you're basically pegged as seeing things very analytically.
So you were talking earlier about, you were talking about the juxtaposition between happiness and honor, even though I don't think they're mutually exclusive personally,
but if there's a situation, let's say, where someone is truly in love with someone else,
and they love them for many years and decades, they have a whole history together,
and then someone, and then one of the people in this grouping, start falling in love with someone else.
So, it's not that there's less love for the original partner, how analytically and emotionally do you take care of a situation like that, when you feel that you want to stay honourable and be happy?
Okay, so the first thing I would say is the devil's always in the details.
Right, so one of the things that I'm not happy about with much modern moral theorizing is that
It takes a story like that, you know, and then tries to extract out a general moral principle.
And often that's impossible, because the particulars of the situation are very important.
But having said that...
Alright, so let me think about that for a minute.
I'm not sure that it's possible to be honorable in a situation like that, because I think that you've acted out the violation already.
And having acted out the violation, to confess it, might be the right thing to do, although perhaps not.
You know, because if you...
It isn't obvious to me that if you betray someone, then you get to have the right to tell them about it.
I'm not saying that.
I know, I know you're not, I understand that.
I'm not, I don't understand.
Yeah, yeah, I understand, I understand.
My observation has been that if There's a tight relationship, and if one party is betrayed by the other in that manner, that it's almost always irreconcilable.
It breaks it.
And, you know, I've helped people try to struggle through that.
On both sides of it, the person who was betrayed and the person who did the betrayal.
I've seen people grow up and not do it again, and this was in situations where their partner didn't know.
And in a couple of those situations, it seemed to me that it might have even been a necessary learning experience for the person who did it.
You know, it helped them develop.
That doesn't mean I'm justifying it, but life is complicated.
But I think that society works better, all things considered, when you make a promise and you stick to it.
And, one of the things I learned from reading Jung, which I really liked, was
You know, he believed that
And he had his affairs too, so you might think about it as somewhat hypocritical, but
But I think that people can make mistakes without having what they think necessarily be wrong
You know, he said that there are things in a marriage that you can't have unless you're all in
And I believe that, I believe that
So if there's a back door open or that like to begin with or a back door opens
Then I think that there's something about the relationship that is lacking at least and I think you pay a big price for that
so I mean it depends on whether you regard a marriage as a Practical arrangement or a spiritual arrangement now really it's both.
You know both are important
But if it's a spiritual arrangement or a psychological arrangement above all then I do think that you don't get the transformation without being all-in and
if you violate it then even if you can work it out with your partner there's something that you will never get as a consequence so last question okay I hope
I'll make this good thanks also for continuing the lecture series I haven't
listened to all of the lectures but it seems like you focus very much on the appeal of the biblical stories to the individual psychology.
Do you have any thoughts on the relative importance of crowd psychology to the appeal and staying power of the Bible and also the
reason why the Bible or the biblical stories took precedence over other ideologies which could have taken its place?
Okay, well let's go to the second one first.
I think it's the same thing that happens when someone
One both creates and edits a great movie
It's no one knows like imagine how many choices are there in a great movie
Let's say it's an animated movie because absolutely everything in an animated movie is constructed everything
There's God only knows how many choices like maybe there's millions of choices
you know and each choice is guided by some intuition of Narrative suitability or beauty or there's some higher ideal
Motivating it right the desire to produce a masterpiece
Maybe that's it that was certainly the case with the Disney movies for example and so that that aspiration then then
Makes the decisions and so I would say well
Something like that guided the writing and the selection of the stories in in the biblical Canon now
Now, could have there been other stories included?
Well, the Catholics and the Protestants don't have the same biblical tradition, and neither do the Jews and the Christians.
And so, it isn't exactly clear what to make of that, you know?
I mean, that's akin in some sense to the discussion we just had about Islam and Christianity.
In some sense, I've left that aside, that specific question, except in so far as I've just answered.
because I'm trying to take what we have, which I know is at the root of our culture, and to figure out what it is that we have.
Why it is that we have it, well I made some attempt to explain that in the manner that I just described, but I don't have a final answer.
Could it have been different?
It could have been different at some levels, but the same at others.
You know, I mean, one of the things that scholars of comparative religion, who haven't been infected fatally with postmodernism, have definitely realized, so Jung, for example,
and Eliade, and people who are interested in grand narratives, one of the things they
pointed out quite clearly is that there's a set of common mythological themes across many cultures, and I tried to outline that in Maps of Meaning, and that worked out quite nicely,
for me at least, as far as I was concerned, because once I had the basic archetypal structure
Mapped out it opened up all sorts of stories to me from all sorts of different cultures
And that's been unbelievably useful like the mesopotamian story of it the anuma elish
When I figured out what that meant as far as I was concerned like I've never forgotten that it just seared itself into my memory and the same with the Egyptian stories
And you know some buddhist writings that I've read in some the dow teaching is also very powerful
So I think that things can be different on one level and the same at another
But that humanity kind of coalesces on what's the same over a reasonable period of time because there isn't that many ways that human beings can live properly as individuals and as groups together
And so there's this constant force that makes our ethical presuppositions converge
And then that's automatically expressed in the stories.
It's something like that now.
It's an imperfect process, and it's full of error
so
Yeah, so
Just one announcement
Well two announcements the next lecture.
I believe is November 14th
So I'll hopefully finish off the story of Jacob looks like it
And then I'm also appearing on a panel with Gad Saad and or an amity on
November 11th, and there's still quite a few tickets available for that
So if you're interested you could go to my website and pick up those tickets.
It should be well.
Hopefully it'll be interesting
I think it will be and might be too interesting
That's one possibility
So we'll see but I'm going to do two more of these this year
And I hope I get through the story of Joseph
And then I can start in the new year with it with exodus
And that's a story that I know quite well and the exodus and leviticus, and what's the one after that?
Yes, thank you
so I'm very much looking forward to that because that is one killer story man, so and
And I've got some surprises for that as well, so
Anyways, thank you very much for coming, and hopefully we'll see you November 14th
...
----
--
...
-- --
50% 50%
Patreon
16:26
...
----
PTSD
-
...
60LSD
----
Eliade
Eliana
potlatch
----
...
Eadwine Salter 912
Banisteria Vine
DMT
MAO
DMTMAO
DMT
MMPI
New Agey
--
...
T.S.
100M103
-
...
-- --
Gad SaadOran Amity1111