Predators are one thing but predatory people other tribes man.
They're brutal.
What about your predatory friend?
Oh, that's pretty bad to the friend who stabs you in the back the person who betrays you
Well, how about when you betray yourself?
Yeah, what's the ultimate predator what's the ultimate predator what's the enemy you harbor in your own heart who hates you
That's the ultimate predator
Dr. Jordan Peterson, welcome to the show.
Hi Chris.
Good to see you
How's the tour going?
It's going great.
The crowds are well-dressed, extremely positive.
They're for good reasons.
Apolitical in the best sense of the word.
Welcoming.
The theatres are packed.
The lectures are going well to extremely well.
the time i spend afterwards meeting people is it's like being in a wedding celebration
i would say that's the closest thing i could what do you mean well you know you go to a wedding and
you meet all sorts of people you don't know generally and everyone's happy to be there and
they're all looking good because they dressed up for the occasion and it's a positive event and
and that's the closest analogy that i that that i can think of that would
describe what's happening so and people that are there are there because they're
trying to put their lives together and they are putting them together and it's working
and so everything about it is as positive as it can be fundamentally so
yeah it's going great I saw you took a trip to the Tesla factory what were your
thoughts after meeting Elon Musk did you get to speak to him much
I wouldn't say much we we spoke probably for 20 minutes in total not purely privately because there's other people
around but you know i just that just barely gets you to know the surface of someone like musk
because he's an amazing person and god only knows what's what's up with him all things considered
we saw his new truck he was taking people out for a ride i i didn't i didn't go out for a ride
The trucks an amazing piece of engineering.
The factory is massive
You know, what do you say about someone who built a functional electric car then shot it into space on a rocket?
He's a singular person, but I thought I thought it went very well.
It was a very interesting evening
so I was pleased to be there and you know, we sort of walked around each other a bit and
It was just fine.
Do you guys interact a fair bit on Twitter?
We seem to yeah.
Yeah
What do you think that is?
Why are you converging?
I don't know.
I don't know exactly
We're both well-known and I suppose to some degree that
That increases the probability of that kind of convergence
but
Maybe he's aiming up me, too
Seems to me.
He's aiming up literally.
He's aiming up very literally.
Yeah, didn't he put a
Wasn't there a spaceman a model of a spaceman in the driver's seat of the car that he put out into space
That's certainly possible.
He's got a theatrical twist
There's no doubt about that and a great sense of humor because that's really funny to shoot your own car out into space on a rocket
That's needlessly.
That's a pretty good joke.
What is it?
That's why is it that someone like Elon has got himself to the stage where he can say things that almost every other CEO,
you know, he's the richest man.
I don't think he's got himself to that stage
I think he's always done that and so now he still knows how to do it.
I mean, you know people think oh
Say what I have to say when I get to the point where I'm protected and secure
It's like first of all being protected and secure does not give you the courage to say what you have to say
That's that's a completely
That theory couldn't be more backwards
You think you're gonna get braver and braver as you get more and more protected you think that's how the world works
I mean, I've watched university professors think that at some point they're going to say what they think as they develop their career
But by the time they're protected and secure they spent so much time not saying what they think that they aren't even who they were
and they don't know what they think so no, he says what he says because he's always done that and people who are like him are like that and
so
Steve Jobs, I presume was exactly the same way.
I mean, I know people who knew him
He always said what he thought and and he was pretty damn cut and dried about it
which is why the Apple products are such miracles of Technological mastery.
He had a unbelievably canny design eye and was very
He cut whole projects
Without a second thought in some sense when they weren't working
He did that when he came back to Apple the second time
Refined the entire product line got rid of a ton of different things and say no forcing on this.
Yeah, right, right
So that was proof.
I mean, maybe it was Luke the first time which it wasn't but coming back and doing it again
The second time showed pretty clearly.
It wasn't same with the same with Elon, right?
He's refined down what he does to a couple of very very tight parameters
Now he seems to have although his hit the enterprise he's put together is unbelievably
High-functioning I mean to produce an automobile sub industry that's actually competitive and to
bring down the cost of space exploration by a factor of 10 and to invent reusable
rockets and to have developed this boring technology it's it's a miraculous
it's probably an alien yeah probably probably there's only two probably a
reptilian isn't American car companies I think that haven't gone bust Ford and
Tesla and Tesla came very close a number of times mm-hmm yeah it's an amazing
accomplishment so go Elon as far as I'm concerned yeah he's a remarkable person
what color skin emoji do you use if I used one it would be black why why not
it's so preposterous all of that you know everything that's happened to
Rogan all this idiocy around race this insistence that we can be reduced to our race, our ethnicity, our sexual identity.
It's so appalling and it's so destructive.
And one of the reasons that I had a lot of reasons for making my political stance in relationship to Canada's compelled speech laws,
I had a lot of reasons for making my views about that known.
One of them was the fact that my government had introduced a bill that required me to say things a certain way, which was an unparalleled
move in the history of Western democracies and something the Americans had made strictly unconstitutional, I believe in 1942.
So that was part of it.
Part of it was I knew that this top-down mandated belief that confusion around gender identity
was a positive occurrence to provide that freedom, let's say.
I knew that for every person that saved, that would doom a thousand people, primarily girls, to a kind of psychological contagion as confusion about sex and gender identity ramped up.
I knew the literature on psychological contagion.
It's quite nicely detailed.
What is that?
What's psychological contagion?
You could think about them as psychological epidemics.
So the last one, the last one of any real size was the satanic daycare scares in the 1980s.
You're probably not old enough to remember that, but the largest, longest sentences in
US criminal justice history were handed out often to women who were accused of late onset female sexual predation of children in daycare centers
The FBI invented a whole new category of perpetrator category that didn't exist because there are no late-onset female sexual child child sexual predators, they don't exist
but there were women who Obtained prison sentences of several hundred years for hypothetically being involved in these satanic daycare
abuse rituals and there was a just swept across the whole country like the Salem witch trials except at a much larger scale
There's a book called Satan's silence that was written by a lawyer and social worker that documents it.
It's just unbelievable.
There were stories about underground tunnels where children were being taken down and being well every possible thing you could think of was happening to them all in the name of like satanic ritual
It was a contagion and those things happen it happened with cutting Behaviors happened with eating disorders.
This is almost all among girls because their teenage girls are most prone to this
They called it hysteria back in Freud's time
But there's a book by a man named Henry Ellen Berger called discovery of the unconscious that traces back Psychogenic epidemics to about 300 years and I knew that
You know people in adolescence, especially people of a certain personality configuration
Have some trouble settling into a stable identity and
For a variety of reasons it can be high negative emotion, which is associated with low self-esteem
Those are more or less the same thing and then in all likelihood high trait openness
Which is the creativity dimension and the high trait openness people
They're the ones that are more likely to have green hair and red hair and lots of piercings and lots of tattoos and dress in a somewhat
in a non standard manner, let's say that's all associated with creative behavior and
They have trouble catalyzing a single identity and then if you throw in categorical confusion
Which is exactly what you're doing when you declare that there's you know, an endless number of gender identities then people who are prone to identity dissociation and to psychogenic Contagion
There you're gonna demolish them there isn't Abigail Schreier has documented that quite nicely and in her book Irreversible damage and
It's way more girls than boys and it's thousands and thousands and thousands of them
so you think well perhaps a few people who are Transgender benefited from this new reality, but for everyone who's benefited and you know
I'd like to see the data just showing how much they actually benefited and that will take a long time to accrue
There is a thousand people who've been just demolished by this
so and then what else on the
Well that that's basically that on the political front I could see all that coming
I talked the Canadian Senate about it when they put in the legislation.
They didn't listen.
They just thought racism bigotry sexism
It's like yeah have it your way
But, you know, so what all these girls that have rapid onset gender dysphoria and disfiguring themselves
and taking hormones and, you know, wreaking havoc with themselves and their families and the broader culture.
These people that were so woke and so permissive, you think they're going to have that on their conscience?
They're on to something, some other noble venture.
So
Give me your thoughts on the modern dating market
Well, I'm too old to really have any thoughts on it in some sense not from a personal perspective
Well, I don't understand it at a level of detail, you know
I I do know some things that are happening perhaps at at universities where
There are far more girls than boys or women than men
What happens in those institutions
This is what it looks like.
Anyways, possibly
So females are hypergamous, which means they'll meet across and up heart hierarchies socio-economic hierarchy, but competence hierarchy is really at the bottom of it and
So when you set up a situation where there's far more women than there are men in a given domain Say where mate selection can take place
Most of the men still don't do very well because most of them are still rejected by women
But a small minority of men do extraordinarily well if you think well means unlimited sexual access.
And so what's happening in the universities is that a small minority of men have sexual carte blanche in some sense.
And most men are in the same position that most young men are always in, which is they're in a state where they're not particularly desirable to women.
And then the women of course are terribly frustrated because the minority of men that they would really like to have long-term relationships with
It's a seller's market for those men.
They're not settling down.
That's the sex ratio hypothesis.
And the reverse happens, right?
That you see whoever the most scarce sex is gets to determine the rules of the game.
So the men, if they are in high demand because there's short supply, you get more short-term mating,
you get an increase in relationship dissatisfaction from women, and when the reverse
happens you get more dates before sex, you get more long-term mating, you also get more
sexual violence in that situation as well when there is a surplus of men and a scarcity of women.
You also get far more unstable societies.
I was pilloried a few years back from my comments about enforced monogamy because they were
taken out of context and twisted in exactly the way that things like that get twisted now.
What did you mean by that?
I mean that one human universal is the construction of societies to both mandate and reward monogamy.
And there's all sorts of reasons for that.
It's because it's the best long-term solution, fundamentally.
But one of the reasons for that is that when women are scarce, men get violent.
Now, you know, that was read to say, well, I thought that this society should be distributing
women to undeserving men which is of course absolutely utterly preposterous and bears
no relationship whatsoever to anything I ever said or thought or anything anyone sane would
ever think or say or has ever thought or said because I don't know anyone politically ever
who was insane enough to think that the state should distribute women to men like that's
just never happened so to be accused of that belief and then for that to you know be put
forward as a credible representation of what I thought was just one of the preposterous things that has happened to me.
It's an unfortunate name, enforced monogamy, because it's a term from anthropology, right?
But what you mean is culturally celebrated monogamy, culturally and norms that are supporting people and raising that up as an institution.
Supporting and punishing both, but mostly supporting.
The punishing is that there's a moral disapproval applied to, say, cheating, to adultery, especially
running around behind your partner's back if you're married, particularly that.
But even if you're in a long-term stable relationship, it's like, well, that's all enforcement.
It's not police with jackboots, but that's not the only type of enforcement.
It's not the only type of sanction or threat or punishment or disappropriation or disgust
or contempt or shame or frustration or disappointment, all of those things.
And all of that, because monogamy is a good long-term solution, but in some sense a troublesome
short-term solution, if you have other options, then all of those elements of social support, let's say, need to be put into place.
And that is, as far as I've been able to determine by looking at the anthropological literature, norms surrounding monogamy are human universal.
There are exceptions, but there are very specific situational reasons for those exceptions.
You see the ONS data that came out a couple of weeks ago that said for the first time
ever since records began, 50.1% of women are childless by 30.
There are more women without children at 30 than there are women with children the first time.
Well, so this is somebody clipped a Part of one of my podcasts.
I believe it was where I was talking about what our society does to 19 year old women or 18 year old women 19 year old women?
we just lied to them all the time, you know, the first lie is there's nothing more important than your career more or less by definition
So that's the first lie.
The second lie is there will be nothing more important to you in your life than your career
So that's the second lie.
And then the third lie is there should be nothing more important in your life than your career so that's the third lie and then
Implicit in that is the idea that children are a burden and that the idea that women should have children is part of the oppressive patriarchy and should be resisted and
And who are men to tell me what I can do with my body and hey fair enough and etc, etc
now I've worked in female-dominated Occupations my entire life.
I work for example, I worked as a daycare worker
Way back when that was like 1980 something like that and there were no men doing that but I really liked kids and so that was fun
and I worked for social services in Alberta in a in the child care department and
Then I've been working as a psychologist
Either training or as a psychologist since then and that's been a female-dominated enterprise increasingly as the years went by but even when I was first
When I first entered it
so I
I'm in the post female in the workplace generation firmly I Never experienced the world
And so I've watched women progress through their professional careers at every level of attainment from the lowest to the highest and observed what happened.
And relatively, I would say bias free because I didn't know.
And what I've seen is that as women progress towards their late thirties, no late twenties, they, there's a psychological transformation.
psychological transformation and what happens is that they place less emphasis on their career and
Way more emphasis particularly on having a child and that really reaches a crisis point around
29 or 30 for the vast majority of women and and their attitude flips and I've seen it flip very dramatically with many women
and I suppose the most signal single most convincing evidence of that.
I worked with high-end lawyers in Toronto for about ten years.
I was part of an organization.
We went to law firms, high-end law firms, and said, send us your most productive people and we'll help them iron out
whatever wrinkles there might still be in their life and the advantage to them is that things will go better for them and the advantage to you is they'll be
even more productive and there's a good management dictum which is pay the most attention to
your most productive people because they're bringing in the bulk of your revenue disproportionately.
And so I worked with men and women who were at the peak of their careers in a very difficult enterprise.
And so these were women who were generally very attractive, well put together physically,
pretty stable psychologically, extremely conscientious, very, very smart, and high achieving from
like junior high all the way through high school, university, law school, onto the top
firms rocketing up through the ranks, full partnership by the time they were 29 or 30.
And all the law firms, all the women bailed out, all of them.
The law firms couldn't keep them.
I was really and I talked to the women a lot about a lot about this because I was very interested in it because I
Knew the law firms were bending themselves over backwards and tying themselves into knots trying to retain these women because why wouldn't they you know?
Just just being greedy capitalists is enough, you know
we don't want to lose their high-performing women because they're performing at the highest level and
They couldn't keep them the women wanted to have nine to five jobs
they wanted to bind the job so they could have a life and that was especially true once they got interested in having a
Child or had one and what what they really came to was a very interesting realization so
because they were highly conscientious women they sort of did their duty and and
Worked hard and diligently and didn't pop their head up to ask questions.
They're in junior high.
They got the best grades
They were in high school.
They got the best grades and so on all the way through
Right till they reach partnership, but that's sort of an apogee right you hit partnership in a senior law firm
It's like you're at you're at the top of your profession
Well, then what?
So then they looked around and they thought hmm here I am with all these like hyper competitive men
Perfectly willing to work 80 hours a week non-stop to stay at the top
What the hell are they doing because that's the real question?
What is it?
What is it that characterizes this small percentage of hyper competitive men?
It's not
You can assume that that's how everyone should be
But first of all, that isn't how everyone is or you can flip that and say well
There's only a small minority of human beings that are willing to do this to work flat out eight hours a week
I mean, they're getting they're certainly being paid for it.
Let's make no mistake about that.
But what about the rest of life?
Well, that's what the women asks
Why am I doing this and that's a great question?
Well for men there's a different answer than for women
It's a really different answer and it isn't like the men are exactly thinking this through
It's it's more like this is an integral part of male motivation
The more successful you are as a man the more women like you but the problem that you have now is that as women are getting
Better educated with more employment more status more prestige
They compete themselves out of their ability to find an attractive mate as women raise up through the dominance hierarchy
And this is competence higher competence hierarchy.
Sorry
Who's going to tell women?
the Equal access to opportunity that you have recently just acquired
Actually, what that's doing is it's making it more difficult for you to find a mate that you're fundamentally attracted
Yeah, well it it it does a lot of things.
I mean it does provide women with a lot more opportunity on the economic front it does
decrease their dependency on their mate in relationship to economic security and educating educating women
Countries that are willing to educate women.
That's the best predictor of their future economic success
So if you look at developing countries and you want to find out what about a developing country is most likely to predict the fact
That they will continue to thrive economically.
It's their attitude towards the education of women and but a couple more things
Women's educational status predicts their children's educational status, but men's educational status doesn't so that's also an important multi-generational effect I Released a video.
I was gonna conclude that other story.
I released a video or someone released a clip of me talking about some of the things we just talked about and
And it went out on YouTube shorts and it's got like 5 million views in a month or something like that
and the comment section is Unbelievably vitriolic is every single comment is vitriolic and it's all from women
It's like who is this old white bastard telling us what we should do with our bodies, you know
And I wasn't being judgmental.
I was just saying exactly what I said to you, which is while I've watched women
Over the entire course of my life with I would say an affectionate.
I you know, I love my sister I love my wife. I have a daughter. I love my mother.
I'm pretty happy about women all things considered
I don't have an axe to grind in relationship to how they should conduct their lives
I don't even know how they should conduct their lives
I've watched what happens and I've also watched what happens to women who hit 29 or 30 and then can't conceive and
That is not Fate I would wish on anyone it's awful and 30% of couples fall into that 30% of couples have difficulty conceiving
It's a lot and the probability that you'll have difficulty conceiving increases with age and so, you know c'est la vie and
but it's very interesting to me to see how vitriolic those comments have been and how how uniform that is because Usually on my youtube channel in particular
95% of the comments are positive and this is completely the opposite of that
so and then so you brought this up at the beginning you said 50% of women now
at 30 50.1 a childless by 30 yeah yeah well you know that's that's not good
that's a sign of something profoundly wrong with the entire culture at an extremely deep level I don't think that women need to take it as us trying to
tell women what they should or shouldn't do but I think that it would be very fair to say that you need to be an incredibly unique woman to make it to 50 without a family
and look back and think yeah i did this right that's not to say that those women aren't out
there they absolutely are i know some of them but i think overall that it's well it's the same with
everyone for everyone i mean this is another example of how our culture has just lost its moorings it's like well what's life well you have a job or a career and hopefully
you're productive and you contribute something to the community and you provide yourself and your family with the necessities of life that's a quarter
of your life or a third of it something like that you have an intimate relationship you have a family that's life and if you don't have one of those
that's one third of your life you don't have now some people maybe they're doing
So well on the other two fronts that they can cope with not having that or maybe they're doing so well on one front
They can cope with not having two of the compensates.
Yeah, maybe
It's pretty hard because if you want to have a great career, it's hard to do that if you're alone and without a family
Right.
I mean the people that I've seen who've been best situated in their life all things considered
Even in relationship to their career have a pretty solid monogamous relationship
relationship that stabilizes them and then they have a family that also stabilizes them and broadens out their life and
you know exceptional people do exceptional things and good for them, but they're By definition given that they're exceptional.
They're a tiny minority
This is always the argument between conservatives and liberals right because the liberal types they're more tilted sometimes towards
What would you call it?
compassion or appreciation for the exceptional
and fair enough the exceptional is necessary but on average
what everyone does on average is the thing to do
and so you just look you see well what do people do
well if they have a job or career they have an intimate relationship and they have a family
and if you don't have
any one of those things well then your treading water harder
It doesn't mean you can't do it and it doesn't even mean possibly that you shouldn't try but as a default
Presumption, it's just utterly foolish
What else are you gonna do with your life?
Well, maybe you're wildly creative
Fair enough, you know, that's extraordinarily rare as well subject to the power law problem in any case
Which is even if you're hyper creative the probability that you're gonna be successful at that economically is extremely
Extremely tiny to the point where it's almost non-existent.
It's so difficult
Now it does happen and some and you can have spectacular success if you become successful
But wasn't it that you did you say last night of the 100,000 most recently printed books only a thousand have sold more than a million
Yes, something like that.
It's something how allows all the way down.
Yeah everywhere everywhere power law
That's you know a tiny minority of people do all the work a tiny minority of people get all the benefit tiny minority of athletes score all the
goals a tiny minority of men get all the women etc a tiny minority of stars have all the mass a tiny
Minority of rivers have all the water a tiny minority of cities have all the people etc, etc, etc
Everywhere always, you know and and we're so clueless in our culture that we blame that on capitalism.
It's like
How does that account for the mass of stars people?
so or the you know the volume of rivers or the population density of cities or
rolling the clock forward you and elon tweeted recently about population collapse
what do you think is going to happen there oh well i've thought for at least 10 years that
the biggest problem in 50 years will be that there's just not enough people i remember
hearing you say a few years ago that you thought we'd peak at about 9 billion yeah we probably
won't hit nine yeah and i knew the stats because think about how crazy it is to think that we
We might be living on Earth right now at a time with the most number of humans that are ever going to exist at one time ever.
Yeah, that's highly probable.
And you know, in the population, the population collapse in developed countries is precipitous, right?
It's like we fall off a cliff.
Because it's the same as everyone knows this from the pandemic, the R-naught number.
If fewer people are reproducing, next generation, you have fewer people to reproduce as fewer people are reproducing.
Well, I worked on a UN committee, oh, it's got to be 10 years ago now, to help draft the UN Secretary General's report on sustainable economic development.
And so I looked at all sorts of things like that.
I was very curious, for example, about, because people have been beating the overpopulation
drum since, well, it really kicked in in the 1960s, you know, because there were dire predictions
By the year 2000, the Club of Rome came out and said,
well, there'll be riots and mass starvation and mass movement of migrants and all the things you hear about climate change
because there's too many people on the planet and that just didn't happen at all.
That was just, it wasn't just wrong, it was anti-true.
It was absolutely wrong.
What happened instead was that everyone got way richer and the bottom section of the population in terms of economic distribution got lifted out of poverty.
Inequality still exists, But that's that power law phenomenon.
We already talked about not that that's trivial
It's just unbelievably difficult to determine what to do with there are solutions, but certainly getting rid of capitalism isn't the solution
and so I looked at population trends and first of all found
Not that this is an act of genius or anything that soon as you educate women at the the size of family shrinks precipitously like below replacement and
That's partly because women have other options that that's a huge play out.
Oh, yes
I mean all the all the countries in the West are way below replacement Korea's way below replacement, South Korea
Japan way below replacement.
Yeah.
I think the number one number one on the planet might be
Chad the country- in terms of growth- eight children on average
Yeah, I think Nigeria will have more people in it than China by the end of the century
So yeah, yeah, yeah and Musk, you know, he's a far-looking man and so he's looking around the apocalyptic corner, let's say.
Uh-oh, we're running out of people.
And what that means, of course, is that you run out of young people, right?
You don't run out of old people first because everyone who is here now is going to be 30 years older in 30 years and it'll be young people we don't have enough of.
don't have enough of and of course young people are the ones who do the
innovation and are going to do most of the heavy lifting etc and so there's gonna be a terrible shortage of young people.
Well you see this with some of the things that I posted that ONS data the 50.1% of women and childless by
30 and both men and women are replying to that tweet saying well good there's too many people on the planet in any case.
I know.
I'm thinking how this NPC midwittery Is so dangerous because it makes people believe that they actually have Something grounded backing up their claims.
Yeah.
Well in this idea that the planet has too many people on it.
This is
There's no sentiment more implicitly genocidal than that statement
So, what do you mean too many people
Exactly.
And what do you mean the planet?
And what do you propose to do about that exactly mass abortion?
Is that your answer or should we do something a little more dramatic?
Maybe we'll just shame people out of having children and i've seen people do that.
Literally.
I saw a professor when I was at an
A ted, I think it was it
It doesn't matter
it was a number of professors talking to a couple hundred students and
one of the professors who was an environmentalist activist type and
he got up on stage and shook his finger to the whole young crowd saying that him
and his wife had only decided to have one child which was in my opinion one
child too many for him and told all the young people there if they had a shred of ethical decency that they would severely limit their reproductive potential
and I stood up and said that I thought that was the most one of the
most appalling things I'd ever heard anyone in academia say to young people
which is really saying something because they say plenty of appalling things and it was a very uncomfortable moment and he huffed off the stage but
You know in a frenzy talking about how you couldn't talk about such things without being pilloried on ethical grounds and yeah, that's for sure you come out as a
what emissary of the academic establishment you tell young people that humanity is so corrupt that they should seriously consider not
propagating because that violates the deepest of ethical norms and you think that's a good thing and that that's you're right and Was just beyond comprehension.
It's beyond comprehension, but it's associated with like a deeply rooted
Existential self-hatred and I mean hatred at the level of
Humanity is like a virus on the planet that we're a cancerous girl except Stein calls this human racism.
Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm, right, right, right.
It's that yeah.
Well, we're a cancer on the planet, you know unchecked growth just like a cancer
It's like that's how I say a cancer.
It's okay.
We know where your heart is Located because what's what's the implications for for a doctrine like that?
What do you do with the cancer?
Cut it out.
Yeah, that's for sure poison it or whatever whatever.
There's nothing you don't do to a cancer
So you're gonna use a metaphor like that.
There's too many people on the planet
You can use a metaphor like that, you know
And then you're gonna you're gonna also decide that you're virtuous while you're using it because you're on the side of the planet
Whatever the hell that means
So yeah, it's it's unbelievable and a huge part of its rooted in this existential shame and and
horror at the condition of being human and the fact that life is rife with suffering and a lot of its unjustified and
You know, it's a Mephistophelean Position so Mephistopheles was laid out portrayed in Goethe's Faust
That's the story of a man who sold his soul to the devil for knowledge.
It's a story of intellectual pride and Goethe stands in relationship to German literature in the same manner that Shakespeare stands in relationship to English literature.
Goethe's Mephistopheles says straight out twice in the play.
Once in the first there's two books and once in the first book and once in the second Gerta hasn't restated twice.
Existence is such a foul thing because of all its suffering,
essentially, that it would be better if it was merely annihilated.
And that's the Mephistophelean stance.
This whole show should just come to a halt.
Look at how corrupt people are.
Evil reigns everywhere.
It's nothing but will to power.
We're destroying the planet with our unchecked ambition, all of it rooted in greed and Machiavellianism and jockeying for position.
we're so contemptible that we should just roll up and die and
We should shame women into not having children and we should shame men.
So they never manifest any planet destroying ambition and it's
It's unbelievably appalling.
It goes all the way down to the bottom
The bottom of things that's what's tearing our culture apart this dispute about the nature of existence at the most fundamental level
So, and the universities have come out on the wrong side.
Talking about the individual, one of the things that I see holding people back is comfort.
So it's easy to get life to a stage where it's not that bad, but it's not that good either.
At least when you have a full on breakdown, there's only one way to go, right?
You're only going to go up from there, but I think it's possible to wallow for years in a just about passable life, right?
Sedated by comfort.
I see this temptation in myself as well to give up the good for the great
What would you say to people who are trying to escape this curse of mediocrity?
Well, if you're satisfied with it in some fundamental sense, I mean, there's there's something to be said
I suppose for walling off a private space for yourself if you can maintain it and
Detaching yourself to some degree from the troubles of the world and maintaining your own little private garden
The problem with that is the snakes tend to seep in from the outside, right?
It's it's pretty difficult to wall yourself off in any real sense from the concerns of the world.
So it isn't clear to me that that's a viable solution.
It also means that you might justify to yourself lack of civic engagement.
You know, I shouldn't go to church.
I shouldn't take part in the political process because it's all so corrupt.
I should hide myself from all the annoying noise that's generated constantly on the media front.
And I have some sympathy for that viewpoint, but I don't believe it's really possible because
you can't have you can't have a walled garden independent of independently of
the health of the broader society it's just not possible maybe you can have it
for a very short period of time but so but if you're if you're comfortable with
what you have and it's Jen it's genuine comfort then I think hey but generally
it's not I think for the most part it's it's people that have become sedated you
know they've forgotten their dreams but they've forgotten that they've forgotten gotten them.
Pink Floyd's Comfortably Numb is about this, right?
They've become Comfortably
Numb.
I think most people... I have this friend and this story really hit me.
So during the pandemic running a podcast, I was able to have the thing that I feel I'm good at, my artistic pursuit and outlet.
That was available for me to continue.
It was actually increased because I didn't have other stuff to do.
I have a friend that's a barber and he got a job at a supermarket.
Barbara's shut down for a long period of time, and he got a job at a supermarket stacking shelves overnight.
And I asked him, I was like, man, how are you finding the new job?
It's a big change.
He's like, do you know what it is?
I actually don't mind the work.
I don't mind the people that I work with.
But man, I miss being good at something.
Right, right, right.
Well, yeah.
Dude, that hit me so hard.
I missed being good at something.
Yeah, yeah, well people need the opportunity to be good at something it so then you might ask yourself
Well, what's the best antidote to the discomfort of life and you might say well, it's comfort
and I suppose that's what you
Act out when you swaddle a baby
But a better antidote is something like adventure to excellence and that's far better antidote to suffering than the mere absence of suffering.
So not to say that the mere absence of suffering, that's not nothing, you know.
Stepping out of that sedation from comforts, difficult though, especially if you've become routinized to it.
Yeah well that's the difficulty of maturity.
You know the Freudians said very wisely that the good mother necessarily fails.
What's that mean?
It means she stops providing the comfort that insulates people against the need for adventure.
I heard you say recently that a mother's ability to let her child
go out into the world knowing that they're still vulnerable and that it's now down to them and the
world to look after them, that's one of the bravest things that they can do.
It's the female crucifixion.
And that's exemplified best in, well the best portrayal of that I've seen is
Michelangelo's Pieta.
It's a statue of Mary and she has Christ's body as an adult on her lap and
he's broken and destroyed and you know she's displaying that and that's the bravery of a mother to allow that to happen but not only that to facilitate it.
So where you go kid?
Where you you go way go well why it's dangerous out there it's like yeah no kidding it's
more dangerous here if you stay with me by a lot so you might lose your body out
there in the world but if you stay here you lose your soul how do you see that
as an individual let's say that there isn't the mother there that's pushing
you along well you know one of the things young Carl Jung was very
interested in the edible complex and that's basically that overprotective maternal.
And he criticized Freud for presuming that it was really something the mother did.
He says it's more relational than that.
First of all, it would be something the father would allow to happen, assuming there was a father around.
So let's not forget about the paternal contribution to allowing that to occur.
Because in some sense, it's the father's role to serve as the antithesis of that maternal over protection
So a woman is extremely bonded with her infant say between zero and nine months and the infant is utterly helpless and so
Complete compassion and the provision of comfort is the only job that matters and that's really the case
And then the woman has to switch gears to some degree.
The mother has to switch gears as the child starts to become more More mobile
fundamentally and more independent she has to let go of the infant which is a real grieving process and
She has to start to facilitate this movement towards independence
but that's a hard shift and so partly the role of the father in that is to be an advocate for the child's independence and to
Comfort the mother to let her know that that degree of security provision is no longer necessary, but also to
Act as an advocate for the child's outgoing
Outgoing desire and so so it's the edible situation is not only the mother
It's also say the weak father, but then it's also the child so you can imagine because you don't believe that these Negotiated agreements were we're relational.
So, you know, you're six you're in grade one
Maybe you're feeling a little ill
Maybe you're not
maybe you're playing with being a little ill and maybe you're playing with exaggerating how ill you are and your mom comes downstairs and says
You know, you've got a test today at school.
Maybe you haven't quite prepared for it.
Maybe you know, you should have and She says but you know you you seem to have a tummy ache
Maybe you're too sick to go to school and the kid thinks
maybe I could just stay home and you know, mom could tuck me in and I wouldn't have to take that test and
I wouldn't have to confront the world and he says yeah
yeah, my stomach really hurts and and away we go and the child has made a choice and
You think well that's and that's a catastrophic choice and you think well children shouldn't be held accountable for choices
They make at that age.
It's like a child soon gonna be an adult that's going to make very similar decisions
The the choice has consequences and to be held accountable for that is to recognize purely that the choice has
Consequences and that it is a choice now, you know
You could say well 95% of the blame is to be put on the mother and maybe that's an overestimate
I think it probably is but
The child could say mom.
You don't have to worry about me.
I'm gonna get up and go do this and
That's choice and
And that's the right choice so these are always chicken and egg problems obviously, but
That that fleshes out the complexity of the situation, you know, if you're if you're being Enticed down a pathological road
You can accept or reject the invitation now some people are better at enticing and some people enforce it more harshly and you know
there's all sorts of individual variability in situations like this, but
But just because you're offered the bait doesn't necessarily mean that you have to take it.
And I'm not a determinist, I do believe that people have free will, whatever that means.
That's a murky subject and it gets complicated the more you look at it, but whatever.
It's still a good shorthand way of describing the fact that we seem to be cursed with responsibility for our own destiny, at least to some degree.
How do you advise people that are dealing with imposter syndrome?
Oh, everyone deals with that.
Every time you make a status shift as you move upwards, of course you have imposter syndrome
because when you first make a transition into a new role, you are an imposter because you're a beginner.
You don't know what you're doing.
And that doesn't mean you're a liar or a fake.
And it doesn't mean you should presume more knowledge than you have.
It's what nature say, every great man is an actor of his own ideal.
That's that's that's that feeds into the imposter syndrome in some sense if you want to move to the next stage at
Some point you have to act like you're already there when you're just barely started and that's not a lie
You know, it's it's the willingness it can be and it can degenerate into a lie
Especially if you presume more than you know, but if you move, you know
Let's say you move from being an undergraduate to a graduate student
Well, every all the other graduate students and the professors know that you're just a beginning graduate student there
They're not going to expect as much from you as they would from a more seasoned graduate student
So you have some leeway that's genuine but you are you know the low-run occupier of that role and of course
You're gonna feel like you're an imposter if you have any sense because you're just barely there you you just made the transition
But that's okay, you know, that's not a problem.
First of all, you have to understand that everyone with any sense who isn't narcissistic feels that.
And it's actually an indication of your mental health and your competence, as long as that doesn't become crippling.
It shouldn't knock you out.
I'm such a phony.
Well, don't be a phony, that's the first thing.
If you're dealing with competent people, and you admit your ignorance, the competent people
Never judge you harshly for that, as long as you've been paying attention.
So, in my classes, for example, people were often afraid to ask questions,
and so sometimes I would point to people and ask them if they had a question, especially the quieter types,
and they'd be afraid to ask the question because they're revealing their ignorance,
and they would assume they're the only person in the room that's that ignorant, but they're not,
because if they were paying attention and they had a question,
the probability that half the class had that question was really high.
That's different if you're not paying attention.
And so you can be ignorant.
You can be an ignorant newbie and you can even ask the questions
that are necessary to ask in that position and sort of reveal your inadequacy.
And as long as you're dealing with competent people and you've been paying attention,
they're just gonna answer your questions.
And then you only have to be ignorant once.
That's the thing about asking a stupid question.
You only have to ask it once,
then you're no longer stupid.
well-balanced people that intellectual humbleness is endearing right really endearing yes so one of
the things that i i want just because they're always asking questions too they always have
imposter syndrome too if they have any sense like what do you what are you more what you know or
what you don't know well if you're competent you know you're more what you don't know and so you're
always asking questions you see someone else asking questions you think oh you're asking questions
you probably are competent so and there's the trajectory that's the trajectory of a person
that will become competent or more competent in the future too right so that what i would hope
with imposter syndrome and this is something that i noticed first off in myself but then in other
people as well um i've bro-science my way into something called imposter adaptation so hedonic
adaptation is the phenomenon where your happiness level tends to reset after a change in circumstances
So you buy a new car or get a new house or get the job promotion and it feels good for a while
But then it resets
Impostor syndrome being that you never feel fully worthy of any achievements that you get in your life
And you don't feel like you are worthy of being there.
Impostor adaptation is a real
Nefarious version of this where no matter how many times you disprove your lack of self-belief
It continues to persist in the real world
And this there is a kernel of truth in this because what you said if you're trailblazing if you haven't done this thing
before but you also have to think well how many times have i done something analogous to this
how many times have i done something that's kind of like this but not not quite this well people
who are high in trait neuroticism are more likely to feel that way because so neuroticism is the
negative emotion personality trait and it's a index of sensitivity to threat and punishment essentially
So imagine that it's very difficult to calibrate how many units of physiological preparedness you should manifest per unit of threat
Mm-hmm, right because how big's the threat and the answer is you don't know
You wake up in the morning and you have an ache in your side
Is that nothing or is that the cancer that's gonna kill you in six months and it's pretty low probability that it's the latter
but the probability is not zero so why shouldn't you be panicked out of your mind and the answer is some people are and
Sometimes they're right
so the calibration of threat especially when it's associated with novelty is virtue and impossibly difficult
Computational problem we have like ten different mechanisms to try to solve that and one of the mechanisms is well
There's tremendous variability in response and if you're higher in trait neuroticism, you're gonna have the problem you're described all the time
you're gonna be doubtful about your competence and the validity of your position and
the only treatment we really know for that is to expose yourself to things that you're afraid of voluntarily and
To become braver as a consequence of doing that but some people have to live with that more than other people
The thing I realized was that
After a while if you continue to disprove your imposter syndrome in the real world.
Yeah, you have a challenge
You're adamant that you probably won't or might not or don't deserve to get past it and then you do
After a while you have to admit to yourself that your imposter syndrome has nothing to do with your capacity and everything to do with
Your addiction about feeling like an imposter.
Yeah, and well and that that does change as people age
Generally speaking they become more agreeable more conscientious and lower in negative emotion and some of that is that adaptation you see that you've
Survive through various challenges and then you can review that evidence to yourself
But also the people around you bolster you because they have confidence in you
and so their anxiety doesn't trigger your anxiety and they'll remind you to
You know, you got this you've done things in such a wealth of data, you know, you've done it so many times
Yeah, and yeah, I think and that and that does help
I mean it does help people get more confident as they get older and they accrue experience because of that
But it's subject to that Underlying trait variability and sensitivity to negative emotion.
I mean there there's been good psychometric analysis of self-esteem scales and
neuroticism scales and they're that pretty much the same thing reversed and
Are you confident in yourself?
Self-esteem you lack confidence
And so it is harder for some people because it takes more evidence for them to dampen down their their response to threat
So and and it's partly because we're all adapted to some degree to the failure of induction
Right, just because something happened multiple times in the past does not mean
Necessarily that it will happen the next time and that's a big bro.
It's the farmer and chicken problem
Right farmers always feeding the chicken chicken thinks the farmers is best friend
There was a stable pattern in the past, you come to rely on it, but at any time that axiom can be disproved.
And so, the fact that we have variability in trait neuroticism is a consequence of the probability of the failure of induction.
It's a very difficult problem to solve, how to regulate negative emotion, you know,
and uh, but I would say that the best way we know is to keep facing challenges voluntarily, pay attention at a rate that works for you,
develop your competence, that actually stabilizes the environment around you, so it's actually, it actually is less predictable and less threatening,
plus you accrue that evidence and you get the social support for doing so.
That's your best pathway forward.
You said that a harmless man is not a good man.
A good man is a very dangerous man who has that under voluntary control.
How should people become more dangerous?
Oh, becoming more articulate is definitely, I would say that's the primary array of weapons.
So, I mean, physical prowess is something, and it's not nothing, that physical confidence that comes along with that as well.
But the same thing replicated at the level of the ability to communicate and to think.
That's a way broader field of battle and opportunity.
So this is one thing that isn't taught well, especially to boys.
It's more important to teach it to boys, I would say, because they're more skeptical
of such the educational enterprise in general, generally speaking, partly because they're less obedient, partly because they're less agreeable.
That's particularly true for disagreeable boys.
And agreeable boys get higher grades independent of their IQ and their academic achievement because they're easier to deal with.
So what do you tell disagreeable boys?
There's nothing that makes you more formidable than verbal competence and being able to articulate,
be able to think, to marshal your arguments, right?
Some battlefield metaphor, get everything in order, get all your information straight to marshal your forces.
And so, I mean that's part of the reason that rap artists are so popular, especially among
Disaffected young men black and white alike because they're unbelievably articulate like they have this
Incredible verbal prowess it's unbelievably attractive, you know, and it's associated with genuine artistic and redemptive activity often focusing on
Something that's approximately the voice of the underclass.
Let's say
But a powerful voice right and it's interesting to see how many young white guys identify with that
Was it Aldous Huxley that wrote Doors of Perception?
Yeah.
So this is kind of an equivalent of that, right?
That you have an experience which many people struggle to articulate.
You take the best of us, the one that has the most precise, most articulate erudite language,
you drop them in and you say, okay, show us what you've learned.
This is the equivalent, but for just a different community, a different sort of life that maybe
You don't have the ability to describe what it feels like to live on a council estate in Manchester or in you know
one of the neighborhoods of Brooklyn or whatever it might be and
Then this person can and it feels like it's your voice.
Yeah
Well, you still if you're a young man, you still feel alienated from your place as rightful heir of the proper Kingdom
I mean that's an existential truism for everyone for every particularly for every young man
because he is an outsider in many ways he's young and juvenile and not very
highly valued and and then is is in some sense hurt by the inadequacies of the
current King the current culture and and is easily turned against it because of
that and that's the machinations of the evil uncle that's the King Arthur story
that's the story of Horace Horace and Osiris it's an ancient ancient story
it's the story of Sauron and
It's there all the time and
You see in that in rap music in hip-hop
the all of that alienation being given an articulated voice in an artistic sense and that's a good example of the power of verbal facility and
That's the route to let's say marketing education to young men
It's like you want to you want to take your rightful place in the kingdom?
It's like get your tongue straight man.
Get it under control in the highest possible sense we went to a comedy club Tammy and I and in New York comedy cellar.
It's a great comedy club and the last comic was an English guy and he was
Not particularly physically pre-possessing and he he made a lot of jokes about that and it was quite funny
And then he divided the audience into five sections and he asked each section to toss up a topic just to yellow the topic
and they were like random topics like the Kennedy assassination and Electric lighting before 1890.
Those were two of the topics and the other three were just as diverse
And then he put on some beats and he did about an eight-minute rap with every verse rhymed and
and
He tied the whole thing together at the end and ended at the end of the music all spontaneously
It was unbelievable and that's logos man.
That's the redemptive power of the logos right there the magic word the sacred word
It's just manifesting itself on stage
There's some very impressive something about that that does feel dangerous as well and not in a I need to be concerned and this should
be contaminated and walled off, but in a way that you think that person has so much competence
that it's flowing out of them and you almost feel competent by being around them.
You certainly feel competent by appreciating it, because it speaks to the part of you that is capable of appreciating such things.
You think, wow, that's really something, that's an amazing display, that's an amazing thing to see.
Amazing, right?
A very interesting word, amazing.
You're trapped and you're trapped by the charisma of that.
And that charisma, that's not nothing, that's a signal of something redemptive occurring.
That accounts for virtually all of the attraction of hip-hop and rap, it's the articulated voice
of the struggling but worthy underclass, I suppose that's a good way of putting it.
But those who are alienated from their rightful place.
And so that verbal prowess is one of the ways they struggle up towards the light.
And that's a good example of having that danger under control, because it's a dark genre in many ways, right?
There's a real undercurrent, an air of violence that surrounds that and its culture.
Like the punk movement in the UK back in the late 70s, same sort of thing.
But that capacity to express that in a poetic manner, in a compelling manner, Johnny Rotten was great at that.
He was so intense.
He worked with PIL afterwards, Public Image Limited.
Is that it?
Public Image?
I think so.
He has a song called Rise, which I used to show my clients all the time when I was starting assertiveness training with them.
I'd put on Johnny Rotten's rise and the line in there is anger is an energy and he's got these unbelievably intense eyes.
Anger is an energy.
You bet.
And John Lydon, man, he could channel that like almost no one I've ever seen.
He'd get that anger built up inside him and then it was completely under control and he expressed it in his music and he's absolutely captivating.
Unbelievably charismatic.
And I really liked his music, that raw anger in the music, but it was in the bloody music, wasn't it?
Wasn't some random riot, you know, he transmuted that into something, you know, you can argue about the poetic merits of
Punk rock, although I don't think you should I mean I Did it my way Sid vicious his version of it did it my way my god
That's a work of genius that it's so it's so brilliantly satirical
What someone's doing is they're refining it they're distilling it down and then they're directing it
So I went to a powerlifting competition a couple of years ago
There was this one guy there lifting, he holds a bunch of records in the squat, and he's a normal working class guy from a normal working class town on the outskirts of Newcastle.
And watching that man warm up is something else.
He's got a sacred playlist.
He never listens to the songs apart from when he's about to step on to the lifting platform.
He's got these headphones on and he's just walking up and down in the same way that you'd
see a bull ready ready to go out ready to go and chase something and he steps
out on stage and the hairs stand up on the back of your neck you're watching
this guy channel rage fury that's the god of war that's Mars yeah he's in
touch with that mmm unbelievable and words man you go to war with words and
you think that's what young men should be taught there we go but a fury um I Want to talk about your recovery
Can you explain how it felt in the first few days when you realized that it might be over when the clouds were lifting?
You know what happened very incrementally over a period of months
Well, things were slightly less catastrophic in the morning.
It was taking me Three and a half hours to stand up and then it was only taking like three hours
So that looked like maybe something had improved.
It was very slow.
Like the question about when did you get old?
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
One day at a time.
Exactly.
So, you know, and I still have a lot of pain.
I mostly feel like I have a
bad flu all the time, but that's way better than it was.
What's changed on the other side of that?
Do you view the way that you should be in world different?
Do you feel like you have a new purpose after being ill for so long?
Hopefully I'm more grateful for the mere absence of catastrophe, you know, and I'm I guess I'm
possibly more pleased to be out say doing this lecture tour.
I mean I was really pleased about it in 2018.
I was already pretty damn happy about, happy isn't the right word, overwhelmed, grateful,
people in a state of constant disbelief, thrilled about the fact that people were responding
so positively, amazed about the fact that this had like a religious dimension,
overjoyed to see people come and tell me that they had got their lives together and that they were very happy about that.
I had all that already, maybe I feel that more.
Now, I wouldn't say that I've learned so much that all the pain was worth it.
But that's, I suppose, in some sense, putting a happy ending on something in a way that's just too trite.
It's like, most of that time I would have far rather been dead for all sorts of reasons.
So now I'm perfectly happy that I'm not.
I haven't forgotten what that was like There's a lot of people that are very glad that you're not
Yeah, well, that's that that's great.
Really.
That's great.
You know, and I'm thrilled that I'm about being able to be
Not terrifying to my family let's say and
I'm really happy to be back out in public and to be
To be doing what we're doing
My you know along with my daughter and my wife and with the support of my family.
It's great
I love this tour.
It's so nice to meet all these people so positive
It's ridiculously positive and in a world where so much is negative and ridiculously negative
That's that's a lovely thing to see and to see these thou I'm gonna see a hundred and fifty thousand people in the United States you know between
When the tour started which was about two weeks ago and the end of I think it's the end of April
before we go to Canada and then to the UK and then to Europe and then to Australia and New Zealand and Southeast Asia and Russia.
All of that's on the table.
And to see 150,000 people who are committed enough to trying to make their lives better to come to the lectures and to listen to them,
even though they're essentially philosophical treatises, or at least the best I can manage in an hour.
And to watch people be committed to this and to hear their stories.
It's
You can't imagine anything could be more positive than that and so that's wonderful if there's something to come back to
After having that it's not much better that you could have arrived back into a world to find no
No, I mean the the the downside of it is that There's such a need for it
You know because part of what I think I have to offer perhaps is encouragement because
I don't think the planet would be better off with fewer people on it.
And I don't think that the ambitious motivations of young men are nothing but the manifestation of the corrupt will to power etc etc.
And the fact that so many people are pining away nihilistically in some sense in no small part
because of such accusations, because they're being taken out by their own conscience.
I think that's absolutely appalling.
And seeing how positive people are in relationship to what I'm doing has that as its shadow,
which is, well, isn't it so awful that that's necessary?
But it is necessary by all appearances, at least to the people that seem to be listening to me.
so c'est la vie and you know, I do believe and I think my family is firmly behind me in this belief that
You know this
The idea that the planet has too many people on it sort of a group idea, you know
There's too many people is like the mass of people
The mass is too big and I don't think of people as a mass
I think of people as individuals
And so there are not there's not a mass of people
it's the wrong level of analysis as far as I'm concerned the right level of analysis is each person and
and I think that that's a core tenant of
The of Western civilization to the degree that the West is actually civilized
let's say the more it's civilized the more the emphasis is on the individual and
and
The idea that the individual is sovereign is the core axiom of Western civilization democracy itself
And I believe that that statement is as true as any statement
We've managed to collectively formulate and so if it's true
then it is the real battle is at the level of the individual or even within the individual and
That's fine with me
And so mostly what I'm doing is attempting to make connections with individuals even though I'm talking to
Thousands and thousands of people.
I'm never talking to them as a group
Ever I don't even look at them as a group.
I never look at the crowd When I'm talking to that my audiences, I always look at one person, you know
It's not always the same person because that makes them uncomfortable
They're happy to be singled out for a second or two, but it's weird if it's a minute.
Yeah, so I'm always looking at you know, one person or another but I'm always talking to one person.
Learned that in part from Kierkegaard, you know
As Kierkegaard believed firmly that as soon as the truth was embodied by the mob
It was no longer a truth
The truth was in and of itself something that was always manifested at the level of the individual
People noticing they know this in their own lives that you have wisdom on your own you go into a group and you compromise that
wisdom for some reason social norms or the way you've dealt with past traumas or the
The things that you think are the people want to hear from you, you know, that's diffusion of responsibility
Right because when you're when you're buried in the mob you can do and say things that that the mob hides from you in the world
Whereas if you're just operating on your own them the consequences of your actions are manifested pretty quickly.
No place to hide so We have to keep you know, every group of people isn't a mob either.
I mean there are groups of people that are decentralized highly functioning aggregates, hierarchies composed of individuals, and that's working at every level of analysis.
That's a properly functioning society.
That's not a mob at that point.
There's a dynamic that permeates the entire hierarchy that keeps the individuals,
let's say at the bottom of the hierarchy, completely in touch with that smaller number of people who are at the top.
A good, a well-functioning democratic political state has that nature, is that there's constant communication upward and downward, just like the way the brain is organized.
The brain's a hierarchy, but information doesn't just propagate from the bottom up or from the top down, even with your visual system.
So for example, when information first enters your brain from your eyes, at the foveal level,
each foveal, that's the center part of your vision that's high resolution, every cell in your fovea is represented by 10,000 cells at the first level of visual processing.
And so there's a tremendous amount of input from your eyes to your brain, bottom up.
But even at the very bottom of visual perception, there's more top-down connections from your brain.
So the visual system is hierarchical, but each level of the hierarchy communicates all the way down the hierarchy.
And a good political system is structured that way.
And so you can have a group of people that's not a mob.
It's a different organization and a democratic polity is not a mob, not if it's functioning properly.
You know, it's something that was really brought home to me when I went to England because
I went into the lobby of the House of Parliament, this great dome building that's more or less at the centre of the parliamentary cross.
And that's where citizens of Great Britain can come and lobby to speak to their representative.
So that's where the voice of the people meets the voice of the representatives.
That's how it should work is in some sense.
There are emotions and concerns that are stirring in an inarticulate manner at the bottom of the
Hierarchy where where the problems first manifest themselves because they always first manifest themselves at the bottom of a hierarchy
those problems aren't necessarily easy to articulate and so people stumble forward with their concerns and
The job of their representatives is to take those stumbling concerns and aggregate them
And to give them voice and to transmit them up the structures of power to transform the laws into the new body of laws
Which is what we act out to to reconcile the bottom with the top and that has to just happen Continually because it's it's a living it's like a living organism
Well, it is in a sense.
It is a living organism because it's a meta organism that consists of living organisms
So, you know for all intents and purposes, it's something that's alive.
I really really hit me in the lobby.
That's where the word lobbying comes from by the way, so it happened there.
Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm, and and people are cynical about lobbying but
People are cynical about lots of things and it's not that helpful
Is it possible to have too much responsibility to take too much responsibility for yourself?
Like one thing I've been thinking is that
But the victim mindset where you believe that you have no control over the outcomes in your life,
I wonder whether there's an opposite where you believe that you have an infinite amount of control over them and you lose faith in your innate ability to just carry you through.
I've been thinking a lot about releasing the tiller, which is a Jed McKenna quote. He's talking about the fact that the best way to ride a boat through a storm is to actually
release the tiller and it allows the boat to maneuver best through the swells.
I think that a lot of the time, going back to the imposter syndrome thing that we were talking about, as you start to accumulate more and more competence,
the higher level of overthinking, the higher level of neuroticism, the more of an attention to detail that got you from 0 to 50 isn't necessarily the thing that's going to get you from 50 to 100.
You had to get across a river and it was bad and difficult.
You don't need to carry that boat across ground to then get you across the next one.
And I wonder whether the opposite of a victim mentality where you take responsibility for the things that occur in life, I wonder whether you can overshoot that.
You can, for sure.
Yeah, definitely.
I mean, you know, Dostoevsky said that every man was responsible for everything he did
and for everything that everyone else does, which is kind of an insane statement, but also somewhat, it's true in a certain sense, you do have an
indefinite responsibility, and you do have an indefinite capacity to bear that responsibility.
But that doesn't mean it can't be crushing.
And then I would say the antidote to that is that you're not in this alone.
As your responsibilities mount, and your opportunities increase, you have to delegate
More and more there's enough for every there's an it's important that you do everything you can but there's enough for everyone to do and
So you might say well
The heroic path is one that leads to universal redemption and that's true and you might say well, that's all on you it's like it is in a sense, but then
The problem that you just described comes all during too much burden.
Well, I can crush you it can be unsustainable You can torture yourself for not doing it.
Well enough and it is up to you, but it's not up to you alone
It's not up to you alone
So you delegate you and you you build you help build people around you?
So that they're all working in the same direction.
It's an effort
It's an effort multiplier in any case and you make sure that they get credit they and I they get
They get credit isn't exact credits good enough.
It's it's not exactly right
the rewards are are Are in accordance with their efforts and you can distribute that, you know
Because there's also a narcissism that can come along with with that which is well
It's all up to me and even if you're working in a very competent manner it can seem that way
But there's plenty of work to go around and there's plenty of credit where credit is due
And so what you do as you attain more responsibility and opportunity is you delegate more of that and you do that continually
I mean one of the roles of a good manager is to make him or herself Irrelevant obsolete.
Yeah, right.
So if you're not a good manager if your company would collapse if you disappeared
That should all be delegated out and it's not because you're abdicating responsibility
Because also what happens is that if you can routinize someone something and parse it off to someone else
So here's a little kingdom for you, and it doesn't have to be little and it's something that can grow
But here's a kingdom for you
Well, then you can go off and do the next thing you need to do which is extremely important
You know and you might think there's there's a kingdom and then it's broken into little kingdoms
And so the farther you are down the hierarchy the smaller the kingdom you get but that's only true if you think the world's
a zero-sum game because you could also think of it as a place of indefinite a place with an indefinite number of the largest
Kingdoms possible and I think what why do we think this is exhaustible in some sense what we're doing?
doesn't look exhaustible you know that's the limits to growth mentality it's like
economists don't believe in that because they think well no we can just get more
efficient which we certainly are we're way more efficient than we once were and
those gains in efficiency when they're not being interfered with are increasing
at more than an arithmetic rate why do you think people have a tendency toward
that zero-sum mentality when I find myself thinking that it's one of the
First things that I check myself on I think that is That is cancer
Yeah, well, I mean there there are elements of life that have a zero-sum element
I mean if you're competing with another man, for example to marry a particular woman, that's a
Zero-sum game if you only think of the game as including you two in that woman
So you can set up circumstances that are zero-sum
But I'm port them across into situations which aren't yeah
well then but to take take that metaphor of zero-sum game where there has to be winners and losers because there's a finite number of
Resources is to assume that the rules of that game are the rules that govern all game the set of all games
And that's just not true.
There's games are infinitely multipliable I mean you can invent a new game people do that all the time the man who invented Catan
Which is a game I really like to play it's a very popular board game that didn't exist until he invented it now
You know thousands and thousands of people play it and he made a fortune from it.
It's like that game never existed.
So there doesn't seem to be any limit to the number of games we can invent and it's a complicated problem because
we are on a single planet and and some resources are more zero-sum than others, but
But we haven't really run into any actual zero-sum limits in terms of our, you know, the probability of us living an abundant life on the planet.
We've stewarded some resources very stupidly.
We've done a very bad job of managing oceanic production, for example.
Although fish farms have alleviated that on the production side to some degree, but it's a tragedy of the commons that we could address and should address, as far as I'm concerned.
as far as I'm concerned.
One of the good things the Trudeau government has done, I think, to give the devil his due,
let's say, is to put a lot of the coast of Canada into marine protected areas.
And that's smart.
We have to be smart about our resources, but that doesn't mean there's zero sum.
And certainly doesn't mean the world is a zero sum game.
And that's a Malthusian idea, you know, that population will grow till it consumes all available resources and precipitously collapse.
And then why do we think apocalyptically?
Well, because things do come to sudden ends
People die people get fatal illnesses like the world you saw carefully constructed can be blown apart at any moment by a random occurrence
genetic mutation that causes the cancer that kills you like life has a like it life has a fundamentally apocalyptic aspect and
We do understand that because we're self-conscious and then it's very difficult not to apply that kind of apocalyptic reasoning to things as such
The world's going to burn up the climates too hot
What about runaway positive feedback loops because that's what the climate types are afraid of.
It's like hey they happen
How do we bind our apocalyptic thinking?
That's a good question, man
That's a good question.
We do that through truth.
We do that with the truth
That's how we do it through dialogue through investigation through exploration through discipline and all of that.
The Logos is the antidote to the apocalypse.
Of course, that's central Christian dogma, isn't it?
That the Logos is the antidote to the apocalypse.
I fancy that.
And so what does that mean?
Love and truth is the antidote to the apocalypse.
Not the planet has too many people on it.
You said to me when we went out for dinner a couple of months ago, I asked you what I
I should be doing with my life and you said what you're doing right now, I think is pretty good and then you said
Truth in the service of love.
Mm-hmm.
What do you mean by that?
He's brought it up again
Well, it's a hierarchy of virtue.
I would say, you know, there's an old idea that God is the sum of all that's good
I don't think some is exactly the right metaphor
It's more like imagine.
There are eternal verities truth beauty justice love
Love, courage, fortitude, compassion, think of all those things as virtues.
So virtue is what all virtues have in common.
Virtue is what all virtues have in common.
That's the relationship of God to the good.
God is the essence of the good.
So let me put that aside for a moment.
You may think, how would that manifest itself in your life?
Well, that might be pursuit of the good and that's the pursuit of the good that unites all proximal goods
Well, what is that exactly well, it's something like the
Belief that it would be for the best that all things flourish to the degree that that's possible
when it when I was a clinician, I thought of that as the good in me serving the best in my clients and
I think the desire for that to happen.
That's love
So that's the desire for, you say, well, you take a human, bent, broken, miserable, malevolent, hurt, corrupt, weak, pathetic, contemptible, frustrating, disappointing,
all of those things that we can lay on ourselves because of our inadequacies.
It's like, it's easy to dismiss that, and part of that dismissal is what drives the
notion that the planet has too many people on it and that we're a cancer on the face of the earth.
It's like, it's not easy to love that, but what do you want?
You want the broken people to rise up out of their brokenness rather than despise them for it, and then you orient yourself towards that and try to pull that out of people and yourself and
You have to have that frame
First that's what you're aiming for and maybe that would be the opposite of hell
This is one thing I would say that unites Sam Harris and I despite our differences in in
Belief in some sense at the level of detail Sam is very acutely aware of the reality of malevolence and hell now
He wouldn't frame that metaphysically or religiously but doesn't really matter
He is doing his best To aim away from that as hard as he possibly can I didn't realize till the last time I talked to him that
Sam identified the religious Tradition the dogmatic religious tradition with the totalitarianism that produces atrocity now
I think that's a misidentification the same way the Marxists blame
Inequality on capitalism inequality is really a problem, but it's not the fault of capitalism and
Totalitarian atrocity is really a problem but to identify that reflexively with religion
Or even with religious dogma, that's a mistake Dogma, maybe but even that's tricky because what's the difference between dogma and knowledge?
you know today's knowledge is tomorrow's dogma and Drawing the line between those two is extremely difficult.
You can't just abandon everything you think even though it's arbitrary you
You need it to guide you and it can transform into totalitarian dogma and promote atrocity in the service of its no longer valid maintenance.
But that's a very complicated problem.
So if that's love, truth in the service of love.
truth to begin with is
Well, okay.
We could take that apart a bit
What you talked about letting the tiller of the boat go?
Well
Imagine that you treat
So we're having this conversation.
Let's say I want this conversation to go the best way it can possibly go
Okay.
Well, I don't know what that way is, but I have to want that to begin with
So I come to the conversation.
I think I'm gonna try to have the most engaging conversation that I can have, I am going to say what I believe to be the case, during the conversation.
There are some things I want from you, except that hopefully we can meet at that event, and trying to crappy outcomes
I don't know what we're going to talk about, you know, we talked a little bit about possible broad themes, although I don't think we touched on any of the things we actually discussed.
That doesn't mean we didn't need to do the preparation, you know, and then you think,
well, whatever we accomplish in the course of a genuine dialogue is for the best and that's to let go of the of the tiller and
truth does that it's like because you can't craft the outcome and so what you're doing by engaging in truthful dialogue is
Letting the wind blow where it's going to blow and you do that if you've decided at some fundamental level
Even if you don't know you've decided that that the truth will set you free and the truth is what is in the final analysis Redemptive and we tend to think of truth.
We tend to think that truth resides in a set of accurate facts
That's actually the weakness.
I would say of the materialistic atheist position that axiomatic
Presumption about the nature of the truth, but the truth is a process
It's it's it's and it's often a dialogical process
So the truth is the thing that emerges in the course of the search for the truth.
It's something like that
And true truth is to be found in the search for the truth.
That's the process that continually revitalizes things.
And so, and then if your orientation is towards the good,
to the degree that your orientation is towards the good
and your belief that the good can prevail,
which is an article of faith, right?
The good can prevail.
It's like, what's your evidence for that?
There's evidence for whatever position you want to hold on that, so it's a decision.
And you let go and the truth takes you away, and you think that it's going to go where it should go.
And you commit yourself to that idea.
And then that's your adventure.
That's one of the things that's so cool about that.
You need this adventure to buttress you against tragedy.
There's nothing more adventurous than the truth.
And in fact, it's the only true adventure, obviously.
You just have to think that through for 20 minutes.
How could it be a true adventure if it wasn't true?
And then why is an adventure if it's true?
Because you're not crafting the outcome.
And so what does that mean?
It means you've decided that the truth is what will set you free.
And that's independent in some sense of the evidence.
One of the things my family has learned, and this has taken a lot of learning, is that
been at least I would say 50 times in the last five years where we thought we'd be taken out by
what was happening around us sometimes those were big things there was probably 10 of them like
they were public and famous and then there was like 40 things that weren't so big but were still
plenty big and it was always the same thing it was hot as hell for weeks but flipped
Always, always, but that doesn't mean it was pleasant to live through the part when it wasn't flipping.
It was horrible.
But so far, so far, we've been able to let go of the tiller and let the waves take us where they'll take us and not flip the boat.
Do you think that there's a usefulness in having a nemesis to motivate you, talking
about some of the situations that you've been through, not particularly those ones exactly
But I try to avoid making enemies of people or groups or ideas or whatever.
Yes, don't make unnecessary enemies, but
There is an extra level of fire that gets lit underneath you when you're going up against someone and I miss it
Sometimes there's a price that you pay for peace
Yeah, well then you just have to look at yourself harder and find the nemesis
Because it's there all the time.
I mean, there's always parts of yourself that you can overcome come and so that's William James moral equivalent to war essentially.
Now if you need something to grapple with and you probably do you can find that you just
look inside you'll find something to grapple with you know inadequacy
weakness susceptibility to temptation narcissism pride envy revenge
resentment frustration lack of faith all of that that that'll keep you occupied
if you really grapple with it and yeah I mean that's an ancient theological
Question, you know, what's up with the devil?
Why why is that?
Why does the possibility of evil exist?
Why is there a eternal adversary see that reflected in Cain and Abel right at the beginning of the Genesis stories?
essentially the first two human beings are Good set against an adversary and that's that's what opens history that story you think well, why would God construct such a
of why would God construct a reality where an adversary exists, and maybe it's because
all things considered, a world with an adversary is a better world.
Just like a garden with a snake in it is a better garden.
These things aren't easy to understand.
No snake, no necessity to contend with snakes.
So why be awake at all?
No adversary, no challenge.
Why be challenged?
Because maybe you're better for the challenge.
Maybe that's the challenge to see if you can be better for the challenge, but that should be internal well fundamentally
well
If it isn't you'll find it externally because you'll demonize someone to turn them into Satan so that you can find an adversary and then
That's very unfortunate for you and for them.
That's just not as big a battle
It's like you you battle with someone external who's malevolent
Let's say or you think they are and usually you've got that mostly wrong, but not always
But if the battle is inside, which is where it's supposed to be
But most fundamentally then
Well, then it's the ultimate it is the ultimate challenge and that's the infinite game
The external one battle between good and evil on a playing field of chaos and order
it's the eternal game and you know, you can play that out in the external world, but
part of what the religious enterprise up is about and
And the Christians have really contributed to this is the notion that that sacred battle is fundamentally spiritual
Which is to say in some sense fundamentally psychological it's to be it's to be fought on the battleground of the soul
Internally, it's a subjective issue.
How do you defeat evil?
You defeat the evil in your own heart
That's that is how you do it
And so if that's all being acted out for you in the world.
Well, you you've misplaced Satan
That's a good way of thinking about it.
This is another weakness.
I think of the atheistic position because
You can it's pretty hard
It's an easy in some sense to dispense with belief in the highest good
But it's not so easy to dispense with belief in evil
So that's a big problem.
So then where do you localize it and you can find evidence of it everywhere certainly in institutions
I mean, that's the whole
Systemic racism corrupt patriarchy narrative is that Satan is to be found at the core of our institutions and to some degree
That's true because everything we do is corrupt to some degree.
And so then do you fight it sociologically it?
you're the good person and the institution is
Satan
So you're so good.
Are you?
You're so sure that are you you've got everything in order or do you and
And you might say well, do you have to have everything in order before you fight evil on the sociological front?
and the answer is well, no because you're never gonna have everything in order, but
You still shouldn't put the cart before the horse
It's really it's a spiritual battle and it's taken people
Thousands and thousands of years to figure this out now.
First of all, it was the snake
What's what's evil?
What's malevolent the predatory reptile fair enough, man?
I mean, we've been fighting with predatory reptiles for 60 million years as mammals 60 million years
So it's a good first-pass approximation
It's the snake the poisonous snake the external enemy the predator
But what about the predator and other people?
Yeah, that's even worse man.
It's like how credit predators are one thing but predatory people other tribes man
They're brutal.
They're brutal
Oh
Well, what about your predatory friend?
That's pretty bad to the friend who stabs you in the back the person who betrays you Judas God.
Maybe that's the ultimate snake
It's like well, how about when you betray yourself?
Yeah
Do you want to see there's this?
Association that's very strange that occurred in the development of Christian thought between the snake in the Garden of Eden and Satan
There's no indication in the original story that the snake has anything to do with the Lord of all evil
It's a very weird
Conclusion that's been drawn.
It's almost extra biblical because there's almost no mention of Satan in the Bible at all
Much less any direct connection between the serpent and Satan.
It's a very very strange idea
But it's part of this psychologization of evil.
Like what's the ultimate predator?
What's the ultimate predator?
What's the enemy you harbor in your own heart who hates you?
That's the ultimate predator
You know and when there's these images of mary
With her head in the stars and baby in her arms and her foot on a snake it's like well
That's the eternal feminine heads in the stars because she's oriented towards the highest good and she's protecting her infant from predators
that could be An actual predator that's been the case throughout not just human history, but mammalian history could be other people who are predators
Could be men who are predators
Could be her
Who's a predator?
the devouring mother
It's like well what what's the ultimate locale of genuine evil
Highest religious answer is that's in you
That's the proper place to battle it out
And I think that's true.
I think that's lit
It's literally and metaphorically true
and I was convinced of that in part because of Solzhenitsyn's writings because Solzhenitsyn identified the totalitarian state with the willingness of
The subjects of that state the subjects and the perpetrators at the same time to live by lies
No, no law no totalitarian state if people don't lie
Every time you lie in support of the totalitarian state, then you're the perpetrator and that's a psychological issue
It's like you're gonna lie to get along or not
Say well, what does it matter?
I'll go along with it.
It's okay
We'll see how it matters because it matters and that's all a psychodrama as far as I'm concerned
Fundamentally when it's properly placed
You've got plenty of problems to take care of on your own front
And that's where you should concentrate your efforts.
One of the things that I've realized is that people that are self-reflective, that
rely on cerebral horsepower, that pay attention, that think in a detailed way, the more nuanced
that you're thinking is, the fewer people are going to be like you, which makes you feel more alone.
How do you think people can overcome this?
Well, I would say that hasn't been my experience, exactly, because as I started to make my thoughts
more public, they seem to appeal to more and more people.
And so I don't know if that's a threshold phenomena, because maybe it is, you know.
As you start to become specialized as a scientist, in some sense, your vision narrows and narrows,
although it gets more high resolution at the level that you're operating, but you kind
of pass through a needle, let's say, out the other side where the thing you're studying starts to become everything again.
And so maybe that's that developmental progression.
Further more.
Yeah, specialization and then
Generalization again.
Yeah, I think that you might be right there, the deeper into the breach thing.
The show that I went to go and see you do in Manchester in 2017 or 18, someone asked
a question about the depth of my consciousness causes me to suffer and you said you take
more of the thing that poisons you until you turn it into a tonic that girdles the world
around you and I think that this is something you see here as well that when you start to
think differently when you start to consider the way that you're living your life in a
more detailed higher resolution more unique more nuanced way you will probably receive
pushback especially you know speaking from personal experience in a normal working class
towns people born live die in these places it's insular there isn't a huge
culture of especially in the UK tall poppy syndrome is a huge problem the
biggest difference that I've noticed actually between American people and
English people is that American children are told that they can be anything that
they want to be mm-hmm they're told that they have blue sky vision they can
achieve whatever they want and that gives them a lot of confidence when us
Brits stuffy stiffer pellet Brits see Americans on TV
It sounds like everyone's had media training because everybody's just so enthused about whatever it is
even if it's a 18 car pile up and then the equivalent in the UK is that
Deviating from the norm is very very very quickly mocked.
Mm-hmm and
There's a lot of that in Canada to tall poppy syndrome.
It's a big deal now
Now the Japanese have that saying too, except it's the nail that sticks up above all the rest is the first one to be struck down by the hammer.
And there's some truth in that too, there's some truth in that, but some and all are very different words.
When you roll the clock forward, what you end up with is American children that then
become adults who look around at the world and say, well, hang on, this wasn't what I was promised.
I was told that I could be anything that I wanted to be.
I was told that I could have anything that I wanted to have.
There's a difference between you can earn everything that is earnable and you deserve everything there is.
So that message can become what you say, it can become misinterpreted in a narcissistic manner.
And I think that has happened to some degree, especially as people have had fewer and fewer children.
You know, Jonathan Haidt and Luke Enough talk about the coddling of the American mind.
they think about that in large part as a consequence of an ideological transformation and
Some of that's true, but it's also useful to look at more fundamental phenomena
People have children when they're a lot older
They have way fewer children.
They have way more resources when they have children on average
You know if you're one kid of eight
You're pretty much battling it out for attention for a very finite amount of parental attention with a lot of intense
competition and the probability that you're going to come out of that entitled and narcissistic is pretty damn low because your siblings will
Definitely punish you for that
but if you're the only child especially of older parents who are also more conservative because of their age and
Also less willing to take chances with you because there's only one of you and then you have a lot of resources at your disposal
Well, that's a whole different.
That's a whole different Developmental milieu and we have no idea what the consequences of that are
But the idea that children in that circumstance are more likely to be over protected and dependent and structured
It's like well, yeah
Undoubtedly, and you know that that would even be an overabundance of parental virtue in some sense, right?
Well, we just did nothing but pay attention to our child
Okay, but too much.
What did you expect?
It's so strange because I'm an only child, right and all of the what?
Well maybe my friends might say differently, but a lot of the commonly held presumptions
around only children, I just, and I have a couple of friends who are as well, and I don't
know whether it's where we're from, that the northeast of the UK is very spit and sawdust,
it's salt of the earth people, it's, you know, grab your bootstraps and your boots and start pulling, and I just haven't, I haven't seen that.
What is it through your clinical practice?
This might not be a primarily working class phenomena, you know, the coddled mind phenomena.
That could easily be a middle class, an upper phenomena.
Is there something, was there a common trend or from your reading have you found that only children tend to be one way or another?
So you just get huge variance in them as well?
I don't know the answer to that at the level of individual psychological data.
There might be a literature, I'm not aware of it.
For me, that was more a response to Hyde's book on the coddled mind.
I thought, okay, fair enough, coddling of the American mind.
What's driving this?
It's not just ideas.
It's a huge demographic switch.
It's a huge transformation in the way we raise children.
We're 10 years older when we have our children now.
That's a lot older.
You know, when you're 18 and you have a kid, you're still a kid.
And there's some wildness that's perhaps not so good about that.
But there's also perhaps a higher proclivity to go off and live your own life.
And then, you know, how much children, how much should your children be left on their own?
The answer is as much as they can tolerate.
And how much is that?
Well, you find out with each child, but it's certainly possible to not deprive your child enough.
So I've realized that it's scary when you find a thing that you're going to fully commit
yourself to the pursuit of, especially if it's excellence that you're going after, because
There's no more room for your inadequacies to hide
Anymore, you can't decide to change direction and do something else if things get tough.
There's no more ejecta seat, right?
I've committed to this.
This is my thing.
This is one of your rules, you know commit to something is
Yeah, commit to at least one thing as hard as you can and see what happens
Yeah, precisely aim yourself in one direction and I had a rule with my clients because you know, you might say well
I've gone halfway down this path and I found out it's wrong
Well, how do you distinguish that from just giving up?
Well, that's a really hard question, right?
It's it's a moral hazard
Because it's inappropriate to continue in a direction you now realize to be wrong
But it's also inappropriate to give up and use that
Rationalization as an excuse and how do you distinguish especially seen as we're not transparent to us?
Well, right exactly
So that is genuinely a moral hazard
so one of the principles that I tried to abide by in my therapeutic discussions was you can change course as long as the next thing you do is equally or more difficult
Because that's a check against just giving up
so
You want to discipline yourself so you can get yourself organized so that you can go in a particular direction
So that when you find the right direction
You can really go in that direction and that does require an apprenticeship of sorts
And it might not matter in some sense exactly what the apprenticeship is as long as it is rigorous
Right, and so that's sort of a bridge between moral relativism and moral absolutism
There's lots of games you can play
It's not that obvious a priori which is the best game.
So that's kind of a morally relative stance.
There's multiple playable games
But then the absolute is yeah, but you have to play one of them
You have to learn to play one of them have become an expert at at least one of them
And then that's not a relative Proposition and I believe that's true.
That seems to me to be the case so you want to commit to something and
Then you you have when you commit to something you
Require yourself to bring all of your disparate disparate components
Moving in a single direction united in a single direction.
So it's a unifying to unifying act and Then once having been unified
Well, then you can bring that unity to bear on a variety of different tasks, but you have to bring it together first
So and that that makes sense developmentally you see children start out
as a disparate bundle of motivations and emotions sort of warring with one another and
And then they can integrate that into single games that they can play with themselves
And then they integrate that with games they start to play with other people
And all of that is integration.
It's not subjugation, it's not repression
Not if it's a good game, it's integration
You want to get integrated because then you have all the horses that are pulling your chariot
Pulling in the same direction
And you're much more likely to get to where you want to go then
And also much more likely to specify a good place to go
So that's something else conservatives have to teach young people, which is, well, get yourself disciplined.
Well, why?
Well, not so you're a slave, but so that you could be a master, to use a terminology that you're not supposed to use anymore.
But, you know, this is in relationship to yourself, not to others.
So, yeah, and to begin with, you have to accept an external master because you just don't
have the wisdom to do that for yourself or the ability or the opportunity often.
Everybody knows this, you know, they feel bad when they decide they're going to put,
get themselves in good shape and go to the gym and lasts like three attempts, yeah.
And then no one's happy about the fact that they quit and they berate themselves for it.
We know that we need to go through a disciplinary process and we need to subjugate ourselves to a disciplinary process
That's part of the problem with the constant harping about the you know, oppressive patriarchy
You need a disciplinary process
so
Well, that's just oppression and slavery.
It's like no it's not
No more than a game is
Not not a good game a good game isn't oppression and slavery
We saw is it being on time being punctual was laid at the feet of some oppressive supremacy.
Yeah, obviously
Yeah, it's utterly
Imbecilic, I mean even at a scientific level
There's no that's trait conscientiousness, by the way to be punctual part of orderliness and dutiful ness
Industriousness, there's no evidence whatsoever that that varies by ethnicity or race
Well supremacy yeah or supremacy and it there is evidence that if you are like that you are more like supreme
Well, you are more likely to succeed.
It's one it is the most
Determinating it's the most
It's the most potent personality predictor of success in algorithmic domains managerial administrative domains
so hard work works and in fact the degree to which hard work works is actually the one metric of of the health of a society
Like the higher the correlation between conscientiousness and outcome the healthier the society.
Well, obviously why well
You want the bulk of the credit to go to the people who are the most productive.
I mean
Not because not even in some sense because they deserve it
Because what does deserve mean exactly?
it is because they deserve it but
That's a black box that word.
It's because if you want them to keep making stuff
You have to do that and you want them to because well or what you don't want food.
You don't want shelter
Why would you not reward the people who provide it differentially?
It's just your own even your own narrow self-interest would require that
so
Talking about committing to one thing and the inevitable pain of they're not being an easy get-out anymore
I've decided that this is my thing.
I'm going after it.
Yeah, it's useful to stick a temporal parameter or an accomplishment parameter on it
That's one of the reasons why
Six months.
Yeah.
Well, I'm gonna get this degree no matter what
Well, it's a time limit.
It's not your whole life, but you're committed to that and then you do box yourself in
It's like well, I'm in this box.
I have to make the best of it.
That's right
You're in this box and you have to make the best of it
So and you might say well, I don't want to be in a box
Like are you so sure you don't want to be in a box a box is a fortress
The walls keep the dragons away you want to be in a box
Paradise is a walled garden
It's not a garden without walls.
It's got walls right you have a house.
It has walls you have a room it has walls
You don't want to be outside of a box pick your damn box and then figure out how to make it into a garden
Well, I want a box without walls.
It's no you don't it's nothing but snakes
Yeah, you spoke about this last night in relation to relationships.
Mm-hmm.
And you said that when you commit to somebody there is the
Inevitable pain that any future
catastrophe is going to need to be worked out in a difficult way between you and the person that you've committed to as
Opposed to you being able to go.
Oh, well cool.
I'm out of here.
The side chicks are warm on tinder in any case
I'm off.
Yeah, right, right, right.
Well, that was something I really learned from reading Carl Jung.
He thought about marriage as
He used alchemical symbolism as
purification
requires heat
Heat and pressure
and so you have a container and it gets hot and
And that's when you want to leave that's when the changes can take place and sometimes they have to be radical to maintain the relationship
Very radical, but hopefully those radical changes are positive
But what makes you think you'd make them if there wasn't a fire lit under you and one of the fires is I can't escape
From you here.
We are locked in combat right here.
We are in this adversarial relationship beneficial.
Yeah, exactly beneficial adversary
Yeah, there's no out except through and there's no evidence that through will work
but and
So that's part of the utility of the vow is to turn the temperature up
And you know you could say well, I'll escape but the problem with that is
Escape to where?
You're not gonna have another relationship, and if to the degree that you brought the catastrophe to the previous relationship
Which is at least a 50-50 probability, right?
What makes you think you're not going to bring it to the next relationship?
You're the common denominator between all of the experiences you have.
Right, I've had many bad relationships.
Like, really?
I've never met anyone I can trust.
Okay.
Ah.
Everyone's motivated by power.
What's the common denominator here?
Exactly.
So, you know, it's tricky because I've,
I mean, lots of people in my family have been divorced,
divorced which is the case in virtually every family and i don't feel like i'm in a position
to shake my finger at people and say you know you failed and with more effort you could have
succeeded that's not up to me to decide and many of those people have gone on to have
more successful relationships the second time around but that doesn't belie the initial point
And besides even the people who went through a divorce wanted to get married again, they still see utility in the vow and the container.
So, you know, you can't make these things into inviolable absolutes.
Zero divorce, zero drugs, zero climate change.
No, that isn't how the world works.
Partly because there's always the snake in the garden, right?
There's no zero.
Not without the application of increasingly totalitarian force has to be some leeway but you don't
blow the whole systems apart just to provide some leeway it's a very difficult thing to negotiate
you know i've had clients who had partners that really couldn't be negotiated with the whole idea
of negotiation wasn't negotiable and i didn't see they really had any choice to either maintain the the millstone around their neck and drown or to leave.
It's an awful choice, but that doesn't mean that marriage is a prison that no one should ever enter.
It just means that things are complicated.
Optimizing for absolutes always ends up in, Cal Newport says this about email, really interesting insight.
He says that one of the problems that you have with anything is when you drive the cost
down to literally zero, you end up with a ton of very weird externalities that you didn't think of.
And he made some argument that every email should cost five pence.
Right, right.
If every email cost five pence, you would receive 90% fewer emails.
Right, right, right.
Yeah, yeah.
The proper, it's very, we've wrestled with that very frequently, building these programs to help people.
So with my colleagues, both of whom are psychologists, one a clinical psychologist, one a research psychologist,
we built personality tests to help people understand their personalities,
Which also produces a couples report so that you can understand the differences between you and your partner at a temperamental level.
And we produced this suite of writing programs that help people write an
autobiography and an analysis of their virtues and faults and a plan for the future.
And, you know, one question is, well, why not give it away?
And the answer is because zero is not the right cost.
Now what the right cost is.
That's really tricky.
Well, that's why you have markets is to determine what the right cost is zero
It's like we've sold way more of these than we would have ever given away
partly because people presume that if it costs nothing it's worth nothing and
Partly because it isn't free like we actually worked
well, one of my partners worked pretty much full-time for 15 years on this at
At subpar wages making a tenth of perhaps of what he could have made in the private domain
Like if he would have gone out and marketed his skills because he's a brilliant programmer.
He has a PhD in psychology extraordinarily educated unbelievably
Accomplished he could have made a fortune in the private in other private endeavors
He worked at subpar wages for 15 years before we had any success on this front at all
So it wasn't free by any stretch of the imagination
it was unbelievably expensive for us to do this and so then to and
Then to say pillory it because somebody might say well if you were really interested in the welfare of the human race
You wouldn't be making money off your redemptive endeavors.
It's like
What do you know about it?
Exactly.
Have you ever tried to build something and market it?
Do you have any idea what that entails?
Yeah, like first of all, have you built something that works that's scalable that would help you've demonstrated that it worked
You've done all that
And that's like you're five percent of the way there buddy because you think now you've got a good thing that people will line up to use it
Ninety-five percent of the problem is marketing and communication.
Have you ever tried to communicate about a product that you've built?
No, and you're telling me that somehow I'm malevolent because I'm trying to make enough money off this to
You justify its existence to make sure that I've designed it in a way that people actually want.
You can tell that because they'll pay for it in a way that will sustain it and allow
it to grow while simultaneously trying to reward the people that developed it.
That's all wrong, is it?
And you know that.
So no, I have a set of empty-headed axioms about inequality and I'm judging you morally
because of their, what, injudicious application, because that's easier than thinking.
That's where that argument goes.
It's just irrational.
Price is an indicator of quality, and it's a commitment device.
It's a rough indicator, but it's better than any other indicator we have.
You know, generally, if you want to buy a suit, a more expensive suit is better.
But not always.
People hack this, right?
Yeah, that's right.
In the online space, they decide to ratchet up the price of something that should have been one tenth or one one hundredth.
I thought this about James Clear's Atomic Habits, it was the best-selling non-fiction
book in the world last year, 2021, and it's great.
And he sold this book for whatever, 8 on Kindle and 12 for a paperback.
If he decided to release an online course of Atomic Habits, 60 days to a new you or
something, it would have been 500 or 1,000.
So there's this odd tension now that's happening between people who have the capacity to improve
other people's lives where I know a lot of authors who are coming into the writing space
from the online course space that they're thinking right okay well I've made the money
now because there is so much disproportionate fee that people are prepared to pay for an online course.
The reason I think this is the case is because people are looking for outcomes with a lot
Of personal development books and they feel that they are closer to the outcome by doing a course because it's going to be more applied
Well, it's also the case that hardly anyone reads and listening and watching is way more accessible to people way more like ten times more and
This is actually going to start it is already affecting that the author market
I would say I mean I talked to Sam Harris about this a while back
But whether he was writing something and he told me I hope I get this right and certainly not a criticism of Sam in any
case, that the opportunity cost is too high.
I mean, look with the video, the video we're making right now, it's probably going to be watched by a million people.
If I wanted to write another book that reached a million people, it would take me two years
of writing, and then a year of marketing, and the probability that will happen even
though I'm already a successful author is still extremely low, whereas we can do this in two hours and reach a million people.
Was it Sam said he's perpetually
Perpetually finding more urgent things to do right something like that, right?
Right, right and and I mean that the degree and the rapidity of communication online is insane.
Think about your
Who was the guy that you did that? What watched you do the lecture series on in Nashville?
He was the Piaget Piaget.
Yeah, right.
How long that take to two half days
Plus prep three something like that three half days plus a week of prep or something right that right?
Right how allows man?
Yes, absolutely.
Well, and and and then there's no leg to publication
Right and and it's an ever-growing platform and it's accessible to ten times as many people and it's just as permanent as a book now
You might say why ever write a book?
That's actually a real question.
It's a question.
I've asked myself because
Some of the themes that I'm exploring in my next book.
I've already talked about in YouTube videos.
Let's say and they've had quite a explosive
Reaction to some of the ideas.
I talked about the nature of the crucifixion and
And the snake the relationship between the image of the crucifixion and the image of the snake
I talked about that on Rogan and that was like two weeks ago
And I think probably 500,000 people have seen that clip like that's more than a best-selling book
Instantly, so why am I writing the book and answer is there's nothing that requires you to think more deeply than to write a book
And so there's still an intellectual advantage to that and a lot of the things that I'm able to say so quickly
Let's say like I did on Rogan, you know, it took 30 years to think because you've wrote those
Exactly.
Well, I find this my newsletter I do it once a week and
It synthesizes whatever I've learned over the last seven days, right?
It takes me, you know a couple of hours to write or whatever and it's less than a thousand words
you can read it in three minutes three minute Monday, mm-hmm and
and
So much of the stuff that I value now that I talk about with friends or on podcasts is something that imposter adaptation
You know that was something I've been thinking about.
I wonder if I can write this right in 500 words
I wonder if I can get it down in casual language, but there's it concrete eyes is what you do
This is why I say people that don't have an outlet where?
Definitely if they don't have conversations
But also potentially if they don't have the right unity to write about what they think about what they think is that you just your thoughts
Just notions.
They're just this it's like a they're low resolution ephemeral very difficult to grasp wishy-washy thing
Put it into words outside of your brain and put it into words say it to someone or write it to someone
See what happens then it concrete izes things.
Well, it also edits it because so when you're writing
part of it is revelatory you write down what you think but
You select what you think from the multitude of revelations
You don't write down everything you think because you can't so you have to select right away and that's editing and then when you
Actually technically edit what you've written the same thing happens you shrink it you you organize it you make it coherent you get rid of
What's irrelevant and so that's tightens up your thinking and then if you're speaking with someone about what you're thinking
It's the same thing because they'll object or they'll reward some of it
And so that's all that dialogue is some of it's the generation of new ideas
But a tremendous amount of it is editing what what's already you've already revealed to yourself in this very vague sort of dreamlike way
Anything you want to say before we finish up?
I'd like to thank everybody who's watching and listening and to thank you and your crew for making this possible
I mean you guys you know
you put a lot of effort into this come over from the UK with your crew and you set this up professionally and and
it's a straightforward interview with no tricks and
So that's not an easy thing to manage and I appreciate the opportunity and that's about that
Jordan Peterson ladies and gentlemen thank you good to see you Chris what's
happening people thank you very much for tuning in if you enjoyed that episode
then press here for a selection of the best clips from the podcast over the
last few weeks and don't forget to subscribe peace
Jordan Peterson
Chris
...
Elon Musk
CEO
FBI
--
ONS
50.1%30
1918 19
**
--
YouTube 500
30% 30%
YouTube
95%
50%
3050.1%
--
10 1000
R0
ONS 50.1%30
NPC
TED
...
95%
Tammy
Logos
----
PIL Public Image Limited
Rise
...
10,000
050 50100
...
6000 6000
----
..
Jonathan Haidt  Luke Enough
...
Tinder
50-50
5 90%
Kindle8 12
5001000
YouTube